<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands spirituall languishing; with the causes and cure: discovered in a sermon preached before the Honorable House of Commons, on their solemn day of fast, at Margarets Westminster, June 28. 1648. / By Thomas Manton, minister of Stoke-Newington.</title>
            <author>Manton, Thomas, 1620-1677.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89499</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M523</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E450_4</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863872</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863872</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161893</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89499)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161893)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 71:E450[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands spirituall languishing; with the causes and cure: discovered in a sermon preached before the Honorable House of Commons, on their solemn day of fast, at Margarets Westminster, June 28. 1648. / By Thomas Manton, minister of Stoke-Newington.</title>
                  <author>Manton, Thomas, 1620-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Cotes for John Clarke at the lower end of Cheapside, in the entrance to Mercers-chappel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf bears an order to print.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached before the Honorable House of Commons at their monethly fast.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161893:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLANDS Spirituall Languiſhing; <hi>WITH</hi> The Cauſes and Cure: Diſcovered in a SERMON Preached before the Honorable Houſe OF <hi>COMMONS,</hi> On their Solemn Day of FAST, at <hi>Margarets Weſtminſter,</hi> June 28. 1648.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> THOMAS MANTON, <hi>Miniſter of Stoke-Newington.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Cotes</hi> for <hi>John Clarke</hi> at the lower end of Cheapſide, in the entrance to Mercers-chappel, 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:161893:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:161893:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE HOVSE OF COMMONS NOW <hi>Aſſembled in Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OU were pleaſed to require my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice on your late day of Fast, as you had done on the ſame occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, juſt a Twelve-moneth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: I deſired to ſpeak <hi>ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably then</hi> and <hi>now</hi> too: The Lord directed my thoughts then to a ſubject of <hi>peace,</hi> our <hi>diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> were great; and now to treat of <hi>Zeal,</hi> our <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> (we fear) draweth nigh. Theſe two things may well ſtand together, <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Zeal;</hi> and if men were wiſe<note n="1" place="margin">James 3.18.</note>, the <hi>fruit of righteouſneſs</hi> might be ſown
<pb facs="tcp:161893:3"/>
               <hi>in peace,</hi> and ſuch <hi>concord</hi> effected between <hi>Brethren,</hi> wherein <hi>Religion</hi> may not <hi>ſuffer:</hi> I know there are <hi>two Parties</hi> that will never be <hi>accorded, the ſeed of the Woman,</hi> and <hi>the ſeed of the Serpent;</hi> there will be enmity: But <hi>is not there a wiſe man among us? not one that ſhall be able to judge between Brethren?</hi> I ſpeak not this to<note n="2" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.5.</note> 
               <hi>flatter</hi> with a <hi>generall offer;</hi> I have alwayes diſliked <hi>generall invectives</hi> againſt <hi>Errour,</hi> and <hi>generall Propoſals</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi>
               <note n="3" place="margin">Qui pacem tract at non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitis conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus diſſidii, is magis animos dulcedine pacis fallit quàm aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate componit.</note>; This were to deale in <hi>names</hi> rather then <hi>things,</hi> and to <hi>ſeduce</hi> the Soul into an <hi>hope</hi> of that, which is farre enough from being accompliſhed. Neither doe I ſpeak it to <hi>cool</hi> any mans <hi>zeal,</hi> the drift of this <hi>Sermon</hi> is to <hi>kindle</hi> it; <hi>Godlineſs</hi> cannot be without an <hi>holy heat:</hi> thoſe that <hi>ſuffer</hi> under <hi>perſecution,</hi> will <hi>contend</hi> againſt <hi>deluſion;</hi> that's but a <hi>duty;</hi> and 'twere to be wiſhed it were <hi>more done,</hi> and <hi>more regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly:</hi> Certainly <hi>ſome</hi> have been too <hi>ſilent</hi> whiles the <hi>truths</hi> of God have been made <hi>void</hi>
               <note n="4" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Naz. Orat. de moderat. in diſput.</note>; therefore we are farr from condemning any ſuch vigorous oppoſition of the preſent Errours. I onely mention it as an <hi>expreſſion</hi> of my <hi>deſires</hi> and <hi>hopes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the preſent <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> the ſtile of it (I confeſs) is too <hi>turbid,</hi> and hath too much of <hi>inculcation</hi> in it, to be fit for the <hi>Preſs,</hi> and therefore I ſhould have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged it to keep company with ſome other neglected Papers; But that in <hi>obedience</hi> to your <hi>Order,</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion</hi> to the <hi>requeſts</hi> of ſome <hi>Friends,</hi> I have now made it <hi>publick,</hi> and (my employment being much) am forced to ſend it forth without <hi>refining:</hi> I doe not know what bleſsing the Lord (whoſe power is uſually<note n="5" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.9.</note> perfected in weakneſs) may ordain by it, I deſire to wait upon him, commending it to his Grace.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:161893:3"/>
            <p>In many things I have freely expreſſed my ſelf, and, poſsibly ſome may think, uncovered our <hi>own nakedneſs;</hi> the <hi>mouth of iniquity</hi> is ſoon opened, and 'tis hard to ſpeak againſt the <hi>Sins</hi> of <hi>religious</hi> perſons, without gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſome <hi>advantage</hi> to <hi>religions</hi> enemies. All that I ſhall ſay to this, is, That <hi>offenders</hi> give the ſcandall, not the <hi>reprover:</hi> I confeſs, I like <hi>rouling in the duſt at Aphrah</hi>
               <note n="6" place="margin">Micah 1.10.</note>, that <hi>Gath may not know it;</hi> but when <hi>offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> are <hi>publique,</hi> 'twere an <hi>injury</hi> to religion to be <hi>ſilent;</hi> we cannot doe it a greater right then to declare and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt ſuch <hi>miſcariages;</hi> and therefore when the <hi>houſe of Jacob</hi> offendeth, it muſt be told its own with a<note n="7" place="margin">Iſa. 58.1. opened to this purpoſe by Mr. <hi>Richard Vines</hi> in the morning.</note> 
               <hi>full throat;</hi> 'twill be our <hi>honour</hi> to ſhake off the <hi>Vipers</hi> upon a diſcovery, though they would ſtill ſtick on: But for the <hi>enemies,</hi>
               <note n="8" place="margin">Horatius.</note> 
               <hi>Nulláne habent vitia? immo alia haud fortaſſe minora:</hi> are they ſo <hi>innocent</hi> as to be able to<note n="9" place="margin">John 8 7.</note> 
               <hi>caſt</hi> the ſtone at us? ſhall they that have <hi>wounds,</hi>
               <note n="10" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Nazianz. de inimicis Eccleſiae, Orat. l. 13.</note> upbraid us with <hi>skars?</hi> and they that <hi>halt downright,</hi> charge us with <hi>tripping?</hi> or the <hi>Blackmore</hi> object ſpots to a <hi>fair woman?</hi> Let them firſt pluck out their <hi>own beam,</hi> and then poſsibly they may underſtand what an <hi>injury</hi> it is, and a <hi>wicked malice</hi> to throw <hi>perſonall guilt</hi> in <hi>religions</hi> face; and out of a diſlike of <hi>one Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai,</hi> to ſeek the deſtruction <hi>of all the Jewes, Eſth. 3.6.</hi> and to charge that upon <hi>the order,</hi> which is but the <hi>juſt blemiſh</hi> of <hi>ſome perſons</hi> ſheltred under the <hi>name</hi> and <hi>pretence</hi> of it; As <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſpeaketh of ſome, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note n="11" place="margin">Naz. Orat. 14.</note> That for ſome Biſhops ſake accuſe Chriſtianity it ſelf as an evill law.</p>
            <p>For your ſelves, (Right honourable) I beſeech you
<pb facs="tcp:161893:4"/>remember <hi>Religion flouriſhing</hi> will be <hi>your defence;</hi> and that it is better <hi>truſt God</hi> with your protection, then to fly to<note n="12" place="margin">Admonendi ſunt pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thores ne dum pacem nimis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligant &amp; cum omnibus quaera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, conſentiendo perverſis ab Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoris ſui ſe pace disjungunt, ne dum humana foris jurgia me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuant, interni foederis diſcuſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one feriantur, Ambroſ.</note> 
               <hi>ill Counſels,</hi> or <hi>condeſcenſions,</hi> whereby you may gain <hi>the reſpects of men:</hi> The Lord grant that you may live up to ſuch a principle; and in theſe Times of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence doe nothing <hi>unworthy of God,</hi> or <hi>of his Oath</hi> that is upon you: So prayeth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your meaneſt Servant in the Lords work, <hi>THO. MANTON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:161893:4"/>
            <head>Englands Languiſhing, WITH The Cauſes and Cure of it, diſcovered in a Sermon Preached at <hi>Magarets Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> before the Honorable Houſe of Commons on this Solemn Day of Faſt, <hi>Iune</hi> 28. 1648.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Revel. 2.3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Bee watchfull and ſtrengthen the things which remain that are ready to dye, for I have not found thy workes perfect before God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N Scriptures wherein the expreſſion is any thing more difficult, wits are moſt ranke and luxuriant, every one taking a liberty to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixe his owne ſenſe there, where the true and genuine ſenſe is not ſo obvious and eaſily found out: and becauſe two or three falſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations may bee aſſerted with equall probability, the Scriptures have ſuffered as an uncertaine rule, or noſe of Waxe, ('tis the blaſphemy of the Papiſts) which is ductile and plyable to every fancy and purpoſe. The truth, is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:161893:5"/>wee are more happy in <hi>diſcovering falſhood,</hi> then in <hi>clearing truth,</hi> and thoſe which come after can more eaſily diſcern wherein o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have halted and are defective, then reach the truth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: I have alwayes looked upon that as a grave obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Obſervatum ſeapius a Wendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lino in lib. de caelo.</note> 
               <hi>Facilius eſt aliorum convellere ſententias quam ſtabilire propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> Men are alwayes better at <hi>confuting</hi> then <hi>confirming.</hi> In which thought I am ſtrengthened by the cenſure of <hi>Hierom</hi> on <hi>Lactantius,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Lactantius quaſi quidam flunius Tullianae Eloquentiae, uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam tam noſtra potuiſſet confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mare quam fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile aliena de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruxit.</note> who obſerved that his arguments were more valid and ſtrong which hee brought againſt falſe worſhips then thoſe other by which he confirmed the true; and<note n="(c)" place="margin">Hieron. Tullius lib. de nat. deo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> 
               <hi>Tully</hi> wiſhed he could as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily <hi>find out the true God</hi> as <hi>diſprove the falſe.</hi> Whether it be through that naturall deſire that is in us, to blemiſh others, or from the weakneſſe and imperfection of our apprehenſions, or from an obſtinate prejudice againſt Divine Truths, or from Gods hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and reſerving many things till the age next their accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment, I will not now diſpute: I onely hint it, to ſhew that therefore it is why men have diſputed ſo unhappily, and with ſuch variety about ſome difficult places of Scripture, alwaies ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitting themſelves with more honour, ſucceſſe, and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>diſproving</hi> the opinion of <hi>others,</hi> then in <hi>vindicating</hi> and <hi>clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> their <hi>own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As this hath been the Fate of other Scriptures, ſo eſpecially of this Booke of the Revelation, wherein there are as many<note n="(d)" place="margin">Quot verba, tot, Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta. Hieron in praeif, ad Bib.</note> 
               <hi>myſteries</hi> as <hi>words,</hi> and all matters (as is uſuall in Propheſies) vailed under expreſſions which are of a myſtick ſenſe and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation. Above all other parts of the Booke the three firſt Chapters are moſt plain and eaſie to bee underſtood, though here alſo difficulties want not: for my part I ſhall not trouble you with the ſeverall thoughts of men about theſe Chapters, the noiſe of <hi>Axe</hi> and <hi>Hammer</hi> ſhould not bee heard in the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> theſe diſcuſſions better become the <hi>Study</hi> then the <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let it ſuffice to note that the main contents of them are ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Epiſtles ſent from Jeſus Chriſt by <hi>John</hi> to the ſeven Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>Aſia.</hi> But here a doubt ariſeth, why a Catholique pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, ſuch as is calculated for the Church in generall, and all ages of it, ſhould begin with Epiſtles to theſe particular Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, what may bee the reaſon of this? Anſwer, 'tis ſo partly,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161893:5"/>becauſe the Goſpel did here firſt eminently flouriſh,<note place="margin">Foxius in Rom. pag. <hi>21. 14.</hi>
               </note> and the Spirit of God foreſaw that the malice of Satan would alſo firſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully invade and over-run theſe Churches, and ſo ingage them to the wrath of God; partly becauſe of <hi>Iohns</hi> particular relation and Apoſtolicall preſidency over theſe Churches, wherein the ſpirit of God condeſcendeth to that naturall inquiſitiveneſſe and deſire that wee have to know what ſhall become of <hi>our owne,</hi> and therefore being about to reveale to him the ſtate of all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, he beginneth with thoſe to whom he ſtood in particular bond and relation.</p>
            <p>But why to the <hi>ſeven</hi> Churches in <hi>Aſia,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">See Aug. de civit. dei lib. <hi>11.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> ſince there were more planted in that tract and country? I anſwer again, it may be part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe of the propheticall perfection of this number which is every where in Scripture ſolemn and ſacred, and with which the ſpirit of God ſeemeth moſt delighted in this Prophecy, and therefore wee hear of ſeven Stars, ſeven Spirits, ſeven Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, ſeven Lampes, ſeven ſeales, ſeven Angels, ſeven Trumpets, ſeven Vials, ſeven thunders, of the Dragon with ſeven heads, the City with ſeven Hills, the Beaſt with ſeven horns, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that the beginning of the Prophecy might carry pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion with the reſt of it, wherein all things are ſet forth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Typicall figure of this number, he writeth to the ſeven Churches in <hi>Aſia:</hi> and partly becauſe in theſe ſeven Churches (which were the moſt eminent) there was found enough to repreſent the ſtate, Graces, evils of all Churches in all ages, and indeed the pattern and Type is ſo compleat and perfect, that by an eaſie and fair accommodation, it may be applyed to all other Churches that are not named here, for in them God was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to give the World a Document and experience of all thoſe judgments and diſpenſations which he would exerciſe towards other Churches offending and declining in the ſame manner.</p>
            <p>One queſtion more, and wee have done with this generall view, and that is, Why all theſe Epiſtles are directed to the ſeverall <hi>Angells</hi> or reſpective Miniſtries of the Churches, ſince the drift of them concerneth the whole body of the people. I anſwer, either becauſe they were notoriouſly guilty of the offences charged, and ſo by example propagated their own taint &amp; prophaneneſſe among the people; or through oſcitancy and careleſneſſe ſuffered
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161893:6"/>corruptions to creep in upon others, or elſe becauſe all diſpenſations from Chriſt were to paſſe through their hands to the Church, and ſo the regular way of tranſmitting theſe Epiſtles, was by means of the <hi>Angel</hi> or Elderſhip.</p>
            <p>Other generall Obſervations there are, but I quit them, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to fall upon the Epiſtle we have in hand. The Text is a part of the Epiſtle to the Church of <hi>Sardis,</hi> which was a flouriſhing and rich City, the Seate of the Kings of <hi>Lydia:</hi> in it you have.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> An inſcription, <hi>To the Angel of the Church of Sardis, write:</hi> you ſee 'tis inſcribed as all the reſt are, to the <hi>Angell of the Church,</hi> that is, to the Miniſtery: who, becauſe of their ſubſerviency to the ſalvation of the elect, and that reſemblance that is between their function and the Angels Office are expreſſed by that term, and though they were many, yet they are expreſſed in the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar number <hi>Angel,</hi> to note their Union and combination in a body and ſociety. To this Angel <hi>write,</hi> in which word hee produceth his warrant and authority. Wee cannot threaten Churches in our owne name,<note n="(f)" place="margin">See <hi>Mr. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſops</hi> Sermon on the Angel of the Church of <hi>Epheſus, pag.</hi> 12.</note> Chriſt muſt firſt ſay, <hi>write;</hi> the <hi>Prieſts</hi> under the Law were to have their eares tipped with <hi>blood, Exod.</hi> 29.20. Chriſt muſt command and inſpire as he doth <hi>John</hi> here, <hi>write.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> A deſcription of Chriſt the Author of this Epiſtle, <hi>Theſe things ſaith hee that hath the ſeven Spirits of God and the ſeven Stars;</hi> the ſeven Spirits, that is, the Holy Ghoſt, who is called ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the plenty, perfection and variety of his gracicous ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and influences; and therefore in the old Hymne of the Church, 'twas ſaid to the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Tis ſeptiformis munere;</hi> and 'tis ſaid Chriſt <hi>hath</hi> theſe ſeven Spirits, that is, hath power to ſend the Holy Ghoſt, who alwayes acteth as Chriſts Spirit with reference to his merit and interceſſion, therefore 'tis ſaid <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.15. <hi>Hee ſhall take of mine and ſhew it you.</hi> Chriſt taketh this title upon him now to ſhew that he had <hi>Spirit enough,</hi> to quicken <hi>dead Sardis,</hi> ſeven ſpirits, when hee writeth to a languiſhing Church. The next part of the deſcription is, <hi>and the ſeven Stars,</hi> theſe are expounded, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.20. <hi>And the ſeven Stars are the Angels of the ſeven Churches,</hi> ſo that the ſtars note the ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Miniſteries, which Chriſt is ſaid to have, becauſe hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointeth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161893:6"/>them, gifteth them, aſſiſts them in their office and fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The occaſion of the Epiſtle, which is taken from the ſtate of the Church, which was well enough knowne to God, and therefore 'tis prefaced thus, <hi>I know thy workes,</hi> a phraſe that is uſed to all the reſt of the Churches, but is moſt proper to <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,</hi> whoſe crime objected is <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> and <hi>pretence:</hi> Oh how ſhould it ſtartle <hi>Hypocrites</hi> to heare God ſay <hi>I know thy workes!</hi> it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth Chriſts ſtrict and ſevere obſervation of what is done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his people, his eyes are every where, but hee obſerveth the Church, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.11. <hi>Hee goeth downe into the Gardens to ſee the fruits of the vallies, to ſee whether the Vines flouriſhed, and the Pomegra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates budded;</hi> phraſes which imply a narrow inſpection.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The ſtate of the Church, is deſcribed two wayes,</p>
            <p>By its repute and renowne among other Churches, they did judge and ſpeak well of her; <hi>Thou haſt a name that thou liveſt, (i.e.)</hi> thou art reputed to bee eminent for Faith Piety, and the power of godlineſſe, and goeſt for an excellent Church in thine owne conceit and the opinion of others; a Church is then ſaid to <hi>live,</hi> when it receiveth the <hi>grace of life,</hi> and expreſſeth <hi>the life of grace;</hi> and <hi>name</hi> is taken for repute and renown.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> By the judgment of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>But art dead,</hi> thy condition is not correſpondent to the report that goeth of thee, the Churches that judge well of thee are deceived, for though there be much <hi>profeſſion,</hi> yet very little of the <hi>power</hi> of truth and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe is found in thee, which is here expreſſed by <hi>death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The next thing obſervable is the Counſell of Chriſt, and direction to this languiſhing Church, and that is in the verſe read. <hi>Be watchfull and ſtrengthen the things that are ready to dye, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which Counſell of Chriſt to his Church you may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 An excitation, <hi>Bee watchfull.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. A direction, <hi>Strengthen the things which remain, which are ready to dye.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. A conviction to ſet on both the former parts, <hi>For I have not found thy workes perfect before God.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The maine duty is in the middle, the firſt part being laid down by way of preparative to it, and the third by way of reaſon
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161893:7"/>and enforcement: therefore though I ſhall explaine the whole verſe, yet I ſhall ſingle out the middle clauſe, for larger and more ſpeciall diſcuſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> I begin with the excitation, which (as I ſaid) was laid down by way of preparation for the other duty. <hi>Be watchfull,</hi> (i.e.) looke to it, ſee whereunto theſe things will grow; ſuch ſad be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings, ſhould make you conſider and obſerve your ſinnes, and provide againſt your judgements; holy-watchfulneſſe and obſervation is the firſt ſtep to amendment, and when people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to underſtand the approaches of wrath, they are in a faire way to prevent them, there cannot be ſuch a <hi>gray haire,</hi> or a ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der intimation of ſwift deſtruction, then a ſecure and careleſſe madvertency; the firſt thing preſſed is, be watchfull.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> You may looke upon the conviction, which is brought as a reaſon why they ſhould watch or recover their former height in godlineſſe, <hi>for I have not found thy workes perfect before God:</hi> whatever men thinke of them, they are not ſo holy and intire as to be able to indure my tryall; things in a Scripture ſenſe are ſaid to bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>full</hi> and <hi>perfect,</hi> when they are <hi>ſincere</hi> and <hi>ſound,</hi> without hypocriſie and guile; and therefore <hi>Calebs</hi> inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity is expreſſed by <hi>fulfilling after God,</hi> or <hi>following of God fully, Numb.</hi> 14.24. he underſtandeth ſuch a perfect and full growth, as keepeth things from languiſhing or dying away.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The next thing now is the direction, or main duty preſſed, <hi>Strengthen the thinges that remaine which are ready to die;</hi> there were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome ſorry remaines of Religion and godlineſſe, to quicken or ſtrengthen; which, he addeth a reaſon <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſhall die; the ſame kind of Greek expreſſion is uſed concerning the Centurions ſervant, when he was at the point of death, which is expreſſed by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> 7.2. they are even languiſhing and expiring, unleſſe you ſtrengthen and repaire them, they are utterly loſt and gone: the word that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth their duty is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſettle or eſtabliſh them; which imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, not only a care to keep them from expiration, but to recover them to their former height and radiancy; and therefore a like matter is expreſſed by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in another word, for he biddeth <hi>Timothy</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtirre or blow up the gift of God in him, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:161893:7"/>
            <p>There is nothing of difficulty in the clauſe, only it doth not ſo eaſily appear (ſince they are not ſpecified in the Text) what are thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>thoſe remaines of Religion,</hi> which he urgeth them <hi>to ſtrengthen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How ſhall we know what they are? <hi>Anſw.</hi> It cannot be meant of <hi>perſons,</hi> as ſome would have it, underſtanding it of the weak of the flock, for 'tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>things,</hi> not <hi>perſons;</hi> and truly it muſt be ſomething concerning the <hi>vitalls</hi> of Religion; ſuch which if revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, would make them live and flouriſh again in the ſight of God and of the Churches; now <hi>Doctrinals</hi> it cannot be, for the reaſon rendred in the latter part of the Text, <hi>for I have not found thy works perfect before God,</hi> it is ſome decay in <hi>practicalls,</hi> thy workes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and if they had decayed in Doctrinalls, they could not have ſo much as a <hi>name</hi> that they lived. And then <hi>meere diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi> it cannot be, for howſoever that be a great preſervation to godlineſſe, and a conſiderable ſtake in Religions hedge, yet the corruption or intermiſſion of diſcipline, cannot ſo properly be termed the death of the Church, 'tis I remember (if<note n="(g)" place="margin">Brightman in Cant.</note> ſome expound the place right) called the ſleep of the Church. <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.2. <hi>I ſleep but my heart waketh. Brightman</hi> applyeth it to the Church about the third century, which was <hi>watchfull</hi> over <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> the <hi>heart waked,</hi> but careleſly digeſted the corruption and degeneration of <hi>diſcipline,</hi> and therefore ſhe is ſaid to ſleep, but its no where called death; or ſo it cannot be <hi>meer diſcipline,</hi> though ſome regard may be had thereunto. And therefore principally 'tis meant,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Reſtauran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes zelum ardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem que pietatis quae in vobis effrixit &amp; pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne jam extincta eſt. Iac. Rex in Apoc.</note> of ſome <hi>few poor relickes of languiſhing godlineſſe,</hi> like ſparkes under the aſhes which needed blowing up; the ſumme of all is, I hope you will be ſtirred up by this admonition to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent your death, and utter languiſhing in Religion, that decayed godlineſſe may have its former power, efficacy, and glory. I look upon the Text as a Counſell to a Church, not to private Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, I confeſſe tis applyed to them by moſt, becauſe it yeeldeth <hi>conceptus praedicabi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> as they call them, much preaching matter concerning the languiſhing and decay of grace in Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>I cannot ſay this is excluded, becauſe the <hi>part</hi> followeth the reaſon of the whole, but I rather looke upon it (and ſo ſhall handle it) in a publick regard.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:161893:8"/>
            <p>The Point is,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>That a ſpeciall way to ſave a Church and people from imminent and ſpeedy ruine is the repairing of decayed Godlyneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis Chriſt counſell to <hi>Sardis,</hi> leſt hee ſhould <hi>come upon them as a thief,</hi> that is, bring a ſuddaine and unthought of deſtruction: give me leave to parallell it but with one place, and then I ſhall proceed to the reaſons; 'tis the counſell to <hi>Epheſus, Revel.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Doe thy firſt workes, or elſe I will come to thee quikly and remove thy Candleſtick, &amp;c.</hi> recovering Religion to its former height is made a meanes of preventing Gods comming in judgement, and 'tis there expreſſed by <hi>firſt workes,</hi> becauſe Religion at the firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming is entertained with more genuine ſimplicity, and zealous earneſtneſſe (as ſtuffes in their firſt making are ſtrongly wrought) and is full of life and power, therefore <hi>doe thy firſt Workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Reaſons,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Becauſe by this means you take away that which will be the cauſe of ruine, God delighteth to make the <hi>outward eſtate</hi> to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry proportion with the <hi>inword,</hi> as we decay in <hi>godlines,</hi> ſo our <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward happineſſe</hi> languiſheth, and the hand of mercy is ſlackened; How eaſily may a wiſe Chriſtian read his <hi>guilt</hi> in his <hi>condition,</hi> and from his <hi>outward</hi> decayes underſtand his <hi>inward?</hi> and truly 'tis ſo in Common-wealths too, their fate followeth the ſtate of Religion, God meeteth to us in our owne meaſure, inſtances want not, <hi>Yee have forſaken mee, and therefore I have left you,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.5. Rulers rebell againſt God, and their people rebell againſt them, <hi>therefore is there a tumult among thy people, Hoſ.</hi> 14.10. Friends are alienated and eſtranged from them, becauſe their hearts are firſt eſtranged from God, there are <hi>confuſions</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> and then what followeth? <hi>deſtractions</hi> in the <hi>State</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Metuendum erit ne qui Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratu conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vente res novas in Eccleſia mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liri caeperint, eodem etiam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnante cum oceaſio ferat idem quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publica mo lian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Theol. Mag. Brit. ſub fine ſent. de <hi>5.</hi> Art. in Hiſt. Syn. Dor.</note>. 'Twas grave ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice which the <hi>Engliſh Divines</hi> gave the <hi>Dutch Magiſtrate</hi> in the Synod of <hi>Dort:</hi> that they ſhould take heed, leſt by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivence at <hi>Church diſorders</hi> which they <hi>could</hi> help, they did not draw on <hi>State-tumults</hi> and <hi>factions</hi> which when they <hi>would</hi> they <hi>could not</hi> help. Truely this is Gods courſe to retaliate with the creature; and (as I ſaid before) to make their outward condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion anſwer their inward. <hi>Religion</hi> is as it were <hi>the Soule</hi> of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:161893:8"/>
               <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> now the ſtate of the body dependeth much upon the good temper of the ſoule, it being lincked to it by the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, as ſo many pinnes and nayles; a troubled ſoule diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſeth the body, but a chearfull mind cureth it: ſo Religion and godlineſſe, as it thriveth, maketh us thrive, God challengeth his people to avouch one inſtance when ever they loſt by it. <hi>Ier.</hi> 2.5. <hi>What iniquity have your fathers found in mee?</hi> and Verſe 13. O yee Generation, have I been a Wilderneſſe or a land of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to you? Did ever godlineſſe doe you hurt? If you can, doe but produce one experience. If you will believe <hi>Polycarp</hi> upon his own tryall, and let mee tell you hee was an <hi>old Mnaſon,</hi> and had much tryall of God; hee'le inform you,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Euſeb Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Hiſt. lib <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For my part ſaith hee, I can ſpeak of 86. yeers, I have been his ſervant ſo long, and he never did mee harm. And truely (notwithſtanding the prejudices that are abroad) wee may come in with the like atteſtation, Godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe never did us harm, when it thrived and was vigorous, wee thrived, and ſenſibly felt the benefits of the power of it. See how God appealeth to men in this matter, <hi>Micab</hi> 2.7. <hi>Are theſe his doings? doe not my words doe good to him that walketh uprightly?</hi> ſee the meaning of that place a little; <hi>are theſe his doings?</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the troubles, doe you think theſe are the fruits of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Or of your indeavours for the advancement of it? No, your own ſoules know that my words have done you good, yeelded you much comfort and deliverance, you were happy as long as you kept in that way. And therefore now if you would take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the cauſe of ruine, &amp; redreſſe the diſorders of the Common-wealth, repair the decayes of Religion, doe what you can to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore that to its former power and efficacy.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Becauſe by outward ſucceſſe, God will viſibly declare his delight in ſuch eminent workes as theſe are, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>ſetteth his beart</hi> to bleſſe and proſper ſuch a people, <hi>who ſet their hearts</hi> to repaire decayed Religion: and God doth it the rather; <hi>partly,</hi> becauſe of the prejudice that is upon godlineſſe, as men caſt moſt <hi>honour</hi> upon the <hi>parts moſt uncomely,</hi> ſo doth God moſt <hi>bleſſing</hi> and <hi>comfort</hi> upon <hi>a deſpiſed grace,</hi> men accuſe it as the onely make-bate, and in the worlds eye 'tis the cauſe of want and ſword and famine, <hi>Ier.</hi> 44.18. and therefore God atteſteth and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:161893:9"/>witneſſeth from heaven that 'tis the onely pledge of a bleſſing, the more wee are prejudiced, the more free is God in honoring it: and <hi>partly,</hi> becauſe of his owne delight in it, 'tis a grace that giveth all to God, and therefore God doth all for it, hee dealeth with it as <hi>Caleb</hi> with his deare daughter <hi>Acſah,</hi> he giveth her <hi>the upper</hi> and the <hi>nether ſprings,</hi> the bleſſings of this life and that to come,<note place="margin">Ioſhua 15.19 1 Tim. 4.8.</note> for as all the motions and tendencies of godlineſſe are to exalt God, ſo all Gods aimes and diſpenſations are to exalt godlineſſe, and therefore is it that wee doe ſo often hear of a bleſſing upon all indeavours, (eſpecially ſuch as are eminent and publicke) that looke that way: ſee <hi>Haggai</hi> 2.19. <hi>From this day forward will I bleſſe you,</hi> that is, from the day that they took care of the <hi>Temple,</hi> God would have them obſerve if their hopes and happineſſe did not thrive from that day forward. So 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.11. <hi>All that came into</hi> Solomons <hi>heart to make in his own houſe and the houſe of the Lord hee proſperouſly effected.</hi> Thoſe two cares thrive the better for one another, the <hi>Lords houſe</hi> made him proſper the better in building <hi>his own,</hi> for God is reſolutely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to let the World know what ſhall bee done to the grace, which hee will honour; ſo ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.4. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the glory there ſhall be a defence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Compare Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od 15 9. with Eheſ. 5.27.</note> by the <hi>glory</hi> is meant the Church reformed or made more holy, for that is the excellency and glory of it; God and his people being both <hi>glorious in holineſſe,</hi> now upon this glory there will bee a covering or defenſive ſhelter, as there was of Badgers skins over the glory of the Tabernacle.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Becauſe this is the ſtraighteſt and moſt direct way to ſafety; in al other policies there are a great many ſerpentine windings and intricacies, whereby the event is not halfe ſo ſure and eaſie, in deſperate caſes 'tis beſt to take the ready way, and that is, the repairing of Religion; 'tis ill when <hi>Religion</hi> is <hi>but policy,</hi> but 'tis as it ſhould bee, when our policy is Religion; though the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles are <hi>by men,</hi> yet out work doth not ſo much lye <hi>with man</hi> as <hi>with God,</hi> wee beginne at the right end, when wee beginne with him, for by making God a friend you may the better get in with men. To ſet on this reaſon, take a few conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Without God men can doe you no good, dependence on the Lord is the beſt ſecurity, and the ſureſt policy is truſting God
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:161893:9"/>rather then men, they are weake and faithleſſe, and ſo will faile you when there is moſt need, the <hi>people</hi> are <hi>unſtable as waters,</hi> and their reſpects are diſpenſed with much uncertainty, to day they <hi>cry up,</hi> and to morrow they <hi>cry down</hi> things; to ſecure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they will deſert them that have done thoſe moſt good: as the <hi>Keilites</hi> were ready to give up <hi>David</hi> after hee had <hi>delivered</hi> them, aſſoone as <hi>Saul</hi> had any force in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.11. if they keep true, their power to help may bee gone, God <hi>kindleth</hi> courage and <hi>quencheth</hi> it at <hi>pleaſure, Ezek.</hi> 7.14. <hi>They have blown the Trumpet to make all ready, but none goeth to the battaile,</hi> for <hi>my wrath is upon all the multitude thereof;</hi> there were great preparations, but their hearts failed them: Truly there is nothing preſerveth States ſo much as Gods power over the ſpirits of men, &amp; nothing which you ought to regard and heed ſo much as that: bodies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hearts are a diſadvantage, and their hearts are in Gods hands; all outward ſtrength and ſupport lyeth in the moveable reſpects of the people, for ſo they are in themſelves, 'tis God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that can fix and make them ſure.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> With God men can doe you no harm, hee is with them that are carefull, to eſtabliſh and ſet up his worſhip and then they need not care who are againſt them, ſee 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28. there is a ſtory of <hi>Sennacheribs</hi> comming up againſt <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> in the firſt verſe, the time is ſpecially noted, <hi>after theſe things and the eſtabliſhment thereof,</hi> that is, after <hi>Hezekiah</hi> had eſtabliſhed the Worſhip of God, which circumſtance is mentioned chiefly to note the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> confidence, for ſee how hee diſvalues him upon this, Verſe 8. <hi>With him is an Arme of fleſh, but with us is the Lord our God.</hi> When yee are thus for God, God will bee with you, and then, what's <hi>duſt</hi> to the <hi>winde? Bryars</hi> and <hi>thorns</hi> to a <hi>devouring burning?</hi> An Arme of fleſh to the Lord our God? All the diſcouragements of the creature come from theſe things, <hi>want of care</hi> to get intereſt in God, and <hi>want of skill</hi> to improve it; your Grand deſign ſhould bee to get God with you, and truely then you may ſlight the moſt daring attempts. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8 <hi>chap.</hi> 9, 10. verſes, <hi>Aſſociate your ſelves, O yee people, and yee ſhall bee broken in pieces, and give ear all yee of far Countryes, aſſociate your ſelves and ye ſhall be broken in pieces, gird your ſelves and yee ſhall be broken in pieces, take counſell together and it ſhall come to nought; ſpeak the Word and it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:161893:10"/>ſhall not ſtand, for God is with us.</hi> In a triumph of faith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet laugheth at their vaine attempts. Hee challengeth not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſingle adverſaries that might ſooner bee diſſipated, but ſuch as were ſtrengthened by a combination of intereſts and twiſted into a league and aſſociation, but all will not doe; <hi>yee ſhall bee broken in pieces;</hi> againe he ſpeaketh to them, call in more ſtrength, come with more adviſed care, <hi>yet yee ſhall bee broken to pieces;</hi> if you will adventure once more and try the other 50 (as that wretched King did) and ſee if heaven will ſmile on a third endeavor, yet ſtill the event ſhall bee the ſame, <hi>yee ſhall be broken in pieces;</hi> he addeth again,<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 1. <hi>chap.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>take counſell together;</hi> that is, recollect your ſelves, ſummon your beſt wits, that you may know wherein you have failed, and play your game the more wiſely the next time, yet (ſaith the Prophet) it ſhal come to nought, your deliberate &amp; mature con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulations ſhall have the ſame event with your raſh and heady en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes, that is, all ſhall bee diſappointed. The Prophet goeth on, <hi>ſpeake the word and it ſhall not ſtand,</hi> that is, when you have prepared the buſineſſe, ſo that you think all the devils in Hell cannot diſappoint you, yet God can, for hee ſupoſeth their preſumption growne ſo confident, as that they ſpeak the word, that is, give out threats and boaſts, and yet then it ſhall not ſtand, the reaſon is rendred in the cloſe of all; for <hi>Immanuel, for God is with us.</hi> Indeed there is the ground of all: God never made a creature or any combination of creatures that ſhould be too hard for him, <hi>God with us</hi> is enough, you doe but ſpit againſt the winde when you oppoſe thoſe with whom hee is, the drivell will bee returned upon your own face, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.18. <hi>Surely they ſhall gather together, but not by mee, whoſoever ſhall ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together againſt thee ſhall fall for thy ſake,</hi> there may bee tumults and confuſions, but being <hi>without God</hi> there is <hi>little hope,</hi> and <hi>againſt God</hi> there is <hi>certaine ruine.</hi> The Heathens were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of this, they would not warre againſt a Nation till they had called out their <hi>Gods</hi> from them, <hi>Macrobius</hi> in his <hi>Saturnalia</hi> hath a chapter, <hi>de ritu Evocandi Deos,</hi> 'twas upon this errand that <hi>Balaam</hi> went to <hi>Balak</hi> to get away the God of <hi>Iſrael, Numb.</hi> 23. Certainly nothing goes ſo neer to the hearts of Gods people, as the inſultations of their adverſaries, when they have loſt their ſhadow and the defenſive preſence of their God, as when <hi>David</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:161893:10"/>had falne ſcandalouſly in the matter of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> his adverſaries boaſted, <hi>now there is no helpe for him in God, Selah. Pſal.</hi> 3.2. and this went to his ſoule, ſo ſtill our ſcandalous miſcarriages give the adverſaries hope that our ſhadow is gone, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In having God, you have men too, hee can preſerve friends, or awe enemies, and therefore ſtill I ſay to gaine the reſpects of men, the beſt way is to get in with God, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.7. <hi>When a mans wayes pleaſe the Lord, his enemies ſhall be at peace with him;</hi> remember Gods power over the ſpirits of men, and then you will ſee that your maine worke lyeth with him, <hi>Jacobs</hi> hardeſt taske was with God, he <hi>wrestleth</hi> with God and findeth <hi>Embraces</hi> from <hi>Eſau,</hi> reconcile your ſelves to God, and take hold of his ſtrength, and then hee can take away the enmity of the crea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure; God can recover loſt hearts, preſerve the reſpects of ſubjects in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire to the ſupreame powers; 'tis very notable that in the 34. <hi>Gen.</hi> the 30. verſe, compared with 35. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. When the miſcarriages of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> had made <hi>Iacob</hi> ſtinke among the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Land, and hee was afraid the <hi>Canaanites</hi> and <hi>Periz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zites</hi> would combine againſt him to ſlay him, God biddeth him goe to <hi>Bethel</hi> and pay his vows. Such dyſaſters ſhould put him in mind of his Covenant; the performing of which was the beſt way to ſupport him againſt his preſent feares: O conſider, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have made you <hi>ſtink in the land,</hi> your buſineſſe is to goe to <hi>Bethel</hi> and <hi>pay your Vowes: Force</hi> will not be ſo great a ſecurity as <hi>godlineſſe;</hi> Armies make long work, but God can ſoon ſtill the <hi>rage of the people,</hi> and when he doth it, it is done in a more kindely way: the <hi>doore</hi> is more eaſily opened by <hi>a Key</hi> then an <hi>Iron bar,</hi> and mens hearts ſooner gained by the power <hi>of God</hi> then <hi>men.</hi> God can cleare up your renowne, recover your glory and eſteeme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, calme the people and cauſe all to be ſtill. There are two things that are of great difficulty, and they are joyned in one ver. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 65.7. <hi>Hee ſtilleth the noiſe of the Seas, and the tumult of the people,</hi> in the accompliſhing of either of theſe things, man is at the greateſt loſſe, either in aſſwaging the <hi>naturall</hi> or the <hi>met aphoricall</hi> waves, and therefore 'twas well done of that King, who to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove his flatterers,<note place="margin">Carut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> that had ſoothed him with the greatneſſe of his command and Empire both by Sea and Land, cauſed his chaire to bee ſet neer the Sea ſide, and the waves beating upon it
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:161893:11"/>without any reverence ſaid, <hi>Loe as great a King as I am I cannot rebuke one wave:</hi> truely no more can Princes of themſelves, ſtill the tumult of the people, for they are both of an equall diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, and muſt be left to the overruling power of God, the noiſe of the Seas and the rage of the people.</p>
            <p>I come now to apply the point, wee have found that getting in with God,<note place="margin">Main uſe, which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</note> by eſtabliſhing Religion, and repairing the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayes of godlineſſe, is a ſpeciall meanes of preſervation.</p>
            <p>Oh then let us conſider this with reflection upon our ſelves, we are concerned in it, <hi>England</hi> heretofore was compared to <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea</hi> for its <hi>lukewarmneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Brightman in Apoc. cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> it may bee compared to <hi>Sardis</hi> for its <hi>languiſhing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wee have a name that we live,</hi> our renowne is gone into all lands, for <hi>ſavory</hi> and <hi>practicall Truths,</hi> but alas our <hi>Crowne</hi> is like to bee <hi>taken</hi> from us, and our <hi>glory</hi> layed in the <hi>duſt! Religion</hi> of late ſeemeth to have loſt all <hi>life</hi> and <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and <hi>godlineſſe</hi> to degenerate into a <hi>cold form,</hi> the <hi>Ordinances</hi> that erſt while were wont to <hi>open heaven</hi> and <hi>breake hearts</hi> through the abundance of <hi>ſpirit</hi> that was in them, ſeeme now to have loſt all their <hi>converting power, Viſions</hi> are <hi>open</hi> and few <hi>gained,</hi> Chriſt is crucified before our eyes, but ſome fatall inchantment and effaſcination ſeemeth to abide upon our Congregations, for few hearts are broken, few brought in to the obedience of the truth. The <hi>Engliſh Chriſtians</hi> heretofore were famous for their <hi>ſevere</hi> innocency, <hi>ſtrict</hi> walking, <hi>conſtant</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, <hi>undaunted</hi> zeale, <hi>ſweet</hi> experiences, <hi>holy</hi> conferences and communications whereas now wee meet with few, but ſuch as are (like the vaine men of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) of a light ſpirit, looſe converſation, given to <hi>vain ranglings</hi> and <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes</hi> more then to <hi>practice,</hi> and <hi>holy life,</hi> and meaſuring Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion not ſo much by the <hi>power of godlineſſe,</hi> as by <hi>form</hi> and <hi>faction</hi> and <hi>ſiding with parties.</hi> God knoweth how unwilling I am to lay open our <hi>ownn kedneſſe,</hi> and to <hi>declaime</hi> againſt the <hi>times</hi> to which hee hath diſpoſed me, I know the nature of man is querulous and complaining, the unthankfull good one will alwayes bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending the <hi>former times,</hi> and accuſing his <hi>own,</hi> 'tis often the voice of diſcontent and peeviſhneſſe, <hi>the former times were better then theſe, Eccleſ.</hi> 7.10. Beſides, every trifling zeale vents its ſelfe in looſe invectives and flings, 'tis eaſy to rake in this puddle, and to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:161893:11"/>reproach our times with ſuch crimes and allegations,<note place="margin">Tacitus.</note> 
               <hi>quae quiſque ſuis temporibus objicit,</hi> (as hee obſerved) with which every one upbraideth his owne age, therefore I ſhall endeavour to make out the conviction more particularly for our humiliation and inſtruction, my method is this. Firſt,</p>
            <p>I will ſhew you wherein <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> is <hi>decayed.</hi> Secondly,</p>
            <p>How it came to paſſe, what may be the <hi>occaſions</hi> or <hi>cauſes</hi> of ſuch a languiſhing. Thirdly,</p>
            <p>What we ſhall doe to <hi>repaire</hi> it, every one in his place, the <hi>people</hi> in their way, the <hi>Miniſtery</hi> in theirs, and <hi>you</hi> in that <hi>orbe</hi> and ſpheare that is proper to you.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> My firſt work is to ſhew that godlineſſe is decayed, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; I ſhall doe that the rather, <hi>partly</hi> that it may help us to put our mouthes in the duſt, and to lye low in the ſenſe of our ſhame this day; <hi>partly</hi> becauſe we are all apt to call our <hi>deſigne</hi> godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, every party like the old <hi>Rogatians</hi> ingroſſe it to themſelves; for my part I looke upon it, as the higheſt <hi>ſacriledge</hi> and <hi>peeviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> in the world for men to doe ſo, to meaſure <hi>Religion</hi> by their private <hi>intereſt</hi> and <hi>opinion,</hi> and as they thrive more or leſſe in the world, ſo to judge or cry out of the riſing or fall of Religion: <hi>private conceits</hi> doe not deſerve ſo <hi>glorious a name,</hi> and the <hi>godly par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> is of a larger extent, then to be <hi>appropriated</hi> or <hi>confined</hi> within any one <hi>Sect</hi> and <hi>faction;</hi> alas! how often doe we miſtake <hi>ſelf-love</hi> for <hi>zeale,</hi> and out of a blinde dotage to our <hi>owne opinions,</hi> think Chriſt ſtandeth or falleth with our private <hi>miſconceits</hi> and <hi>inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts!</hi> It was but a preſumptuous arrogance in <hi>Neſtorius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſperde me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum haereticos &amp; ego tecum diſperdam Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas, &amp;c.</note> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe heaven and victory ſo laviſhly to <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperour, if he would doe as he ſuggeſted; therefore to prevent all partiall claims, &amp; to wave the ſuſpition of any ſuch drift, I ſhal firſt ſhew wherein the power of godlineſſe is found to decay and languiſh even unto death, I meane that godlineſſe which is commended to us in the word, and is the glory of our Religion and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the gaſping of it is many waies diſcovered, but eſpecially by theſe things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> By the languiſhing of <hi>zeale,</hi> and the neglect of publick duties. Zeal is a grace ſo rare, that we ſcarce know the nature and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it; for alas, to what a <hi>ſtupidneſſe</hi> and <hi>cold indifferency</hi> in Religion are we come! though God be diſhonored, <hi>truth</hi> violated,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:161893:12"/>the <hi>Sabbath</hi> prophaned, yet men are neither hot nor cold, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.15. we content our ſelves with a lukewarmneſſe and mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of profeſſion, midling it between Chriſt and the world, neither <hi>ſuffering,</hi> nor <hi>doing</hi> any further then will ſuite with our <hi>intereſts,</hi> as if in hazardous caſes we ſhould <hi>locke on</hi> rather then <hi>interpoſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude 3.</hi> Non amat qui non Lelat. Aug. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntra Adi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant. cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> Where are thoſe that doe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>contend earneſtly for the faith of the Saints?</hi> the glory of God? that mind Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for Religions ſake? if we had more love, wee would have more zeale, if the heart were gained to <hi>Religion,</hi> we would have more <hi>heat</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> and not give up our ſelves to ſuch a <hi>ſecure oſcitancy;</hi> the <hi>iniquity</hi> of the times ſhould put us <hi>forward,</hi> not make us <hi>worſe;</hi> A godly man ſhould be like <hi>fountaine water, hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt</hi> in <hi>cold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt weather; dead</hi> fiſhes may ſwimme with the <hi>ſtreame,</hi> and every <hi>carnall</hi> heart walke according to the <hi>trade</hi> of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> it deſerveth no thankes to be earneſt in duties, when there is no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition againſt them, but alas, as ſoone as danger commeth, how are men diſcouraged! it ſhould not be ſo, when the wicked prevaile, it's ſaid of the godly man, <hi>Job</hi> 17.9. <hi>that hee ſhall hold on his way, and hee that is righteous grow ſtronger and ſtronger:</hi> true grace and true zeale by an Antiperiſtaſis is <hi>beſt</hi> in the <hi>worſt</hi> times, but it's otherwiſe with us, for our <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> ſome of them, when the day of God is prophaned, his name diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, his truth queſtioned, are like careleſſe <hi>Gallio's,</hi> troubled with none of theſe things, doe not come forth to the helpe of Chriſt; for our <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> many act no further then they are <hi>incouraged,</hi> and <hi>put on</hi> by an <hi>outward power,</hi> and will not ingage till all <hi>diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties</hi> be firſt removed by a <hi>ſecular arme;</hi> others leave themſelves at a looſe liberty and indifferency to comply with all parties, and launch forth no further, then they may get to ſhore again if a ſtorm ariſe; our <hi>people</hi> are in an unſetled heſitation ready to draw back upon every trouble, pleading for the <hi>ſtumps of Dagon,</hi> and revolting in their hearts to the <hi>old wayes:</hi> and truly as yet the evill dayes are not fully come, ſo that this grace is not thorowly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, however a <hi>cold ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fferency</hi> in ſuch times, will in very e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill times be a <hi>flat Apoſtaſie;</hi> certainly this is clear already, that we are much gone off from our <hi>firſt love:</hi> At the <hi>firſt breaking out of Reformation,</hi> what heat and violence was there offered to the Kingdome of God? what zeale againſt the <hi>little foxes?</hi> every
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:161893:12"/>modeſt appearance of errour? what an holy ſorwardneſſe?<note place="margin">Metuendum eſt in poſtrem mundi aetate magis hunc er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorem graſſatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram eſſe, quodaut nihil ſint Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giones eut diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant tantum vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabulis, Melanc. poſtil. de Bapt. Chriſti.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as now we are at a ſtand, the old world (like old men) every day loſing more of its heat and fervour; <hi>Melancthons</hi> prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is almoſt verified, for he (though he were a ſober and meek man, and indeed his fault was too much connivence, for by his ſilence <hi>Conſubſtantiation</hi> prevailed) was ſo ſenſible of the decay of zeal in his time, that he feared the world would come to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Religion a matter of nothing, or a word-ſtrife not worthy mens regard and engagement, and truly it's even brought to that paſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> By the <hi>inſipid formality</hi> and <hi>dead heartedneſſe,</hi> that is found e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where, we are without life in the wayes of God, little beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of holineſſe, little circumſpection and ſtrictneſſe in life and converſation: <hi>Religion</hi> is like a <hi>river,</hi> it loſeth in <hi>ſtrength</hi> what it getteth in <hi>breadth,</hi> now many come in, to profeſſe, their wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings are not ſo awfull and ſevere; when it's a <hi>ſhame</hi> not to have ſome forme in Religion, many have but a forme, and do debaſe the holy profeſſion, by mingling it with their pride, luſt and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varice, ſo that it's not ſo <hi>daunting</hi> and hath no ſuch <hi>Majeſty</hi> with it as formerly it had; a <hi>truly godly man</hi> is to be the worlds <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> the worlds <hi>reproofe,</hi> the worlds <hi>conviction,</hi> the worlds <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> 1 <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</hi> 4.4. <hi>they thinke ſtrange,</hi> &amp;c. you are to hold forth ſuch <hi>mortification</hi> and <hi>ſelfe-deniall,</hi> that the world may wonder; you are to weane your ſelves, and bind up your affections from ſuch ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects as do ſo pleaſantly and powerfully inſinuate with them, and raviſh their affections; he ſhould be too the worlds <hi>reproofe, Heb.</hi> 11.7. by building an Arke <hi>Noah</hi> condemned the world, you ſhould be <hi>Mirrours</hi> to kill <hi>Baſiliskes,</hi> and in the <hi>innocency</hi> of your lives, ſhew them their owne <hi>filthineſſe;</hi> in ſhort, your lives ſhould be a <hi>reall reproofe</hi> and upbraiding to them; and then the worlds <hi>conviction,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.25. you ſhould walke ſo, that they may ſee <hi>God in you of a truth,</hi> your <hi>converſation</hi> ſhould be nothing elſe but a <hi>walking rule,</hi> and <hi>Religion exemplified;</hi> but alas, how vaine, carnall, ſenſuall, are moſt men, diſcovering nothing of the power of grace, the beautie of holineſſe, and the efficacy of the new-nature, we may ſee much of <hi>man,</hi> but nothing of <hi>God</hi> in them, its even our deſcription, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. <hi>having a forme of godlineſſe but denying the power thereof: denying the power,</hi> that is,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:161893:13"/>refuſing and reſiſting that inward virtue and force of godlineſſe, by which the heart ſhould be renewed or the converſation recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Poſſibly there may be more <hi>light</hi> but leſſe <hi>heat,</hi> what <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> obſerved of his times is true of ours, <hi>Bonieſſe deſierunt, ſicubi docti evaſerint,</hi> they were leſſe good when they were more learned: for now we rather <hi>diſpute</hi> away duties then <hi>practiſe</hi> them. Oh! 'tis ſad, this, when <hi>knowledge</hi> ſhall devour <hi>good life</hi> and <hi>notion</hi> ſpoile <hi>knowledge;</hi> that of <hi>Hugo</hi> is but too juſt a <hi>character</hi> of us, <hi>Amant lection<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hugo lib. <hi>2.</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcel. cap. <hi>52.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>non Religionem, immo amore lectionis in odium incidunt Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis, mul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os video ſtudioſos, paucos religioſos,</hi> &amp;c. many deſire to know, few to live, yea knowledge ſeemth to make men leſſe ſtrict and holy, for they diſpute away Religion, the more they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand of it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>Loathing of heavenly Manna,</hi> there cannot be a more proper diſcovery of ſpirituall languiſhing, ſick perſons loath their food, and feed upon aſhes;<note place="margin">See <hi>Shepards</hi> Sound beſeever. pag. 250.</note> ſurely godlineſſe is in the Wane when a people are <hi>Chriſt-glutted,</hi> and <hi>Goſpel-glutted,</hi> and are all for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded <hi>ſubtleties, quinteſſentiall extracts</hi> and <hi>diſtillations:</hi> Oh how welcome were the <hi>firſt appearances</hi> of light! tis a bleſſing we know by the want of it; when we came newly out of darknes, whoſe heart did not ſay within him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, welcome ſweet light? when it was a <hi>new thing,</hi> how ſtrangely did it affectus? but 'tis the unhappy fate of the Word to be diſpiſed upon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, <hi>John</hi> 16.35. <hi>Yee rejoyced in his light,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for a ſeaſon,<note place="margin">1 Cant. 26.</note> ſome ſmall time, when firſt hee began to ſhine in their borders; to a <hi>gracious eye</hi> truths bed is <hi>alwaies green,</hi> as freſh and flouriſhing at the laſt as at the beginning, but moſt looke upon it with an <hi>adulterous</hi> eye and heart, love it whilſt 'tis <hi>new,</hi> nauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate it after ſome acquaintance and knowledge of it; with what faſtidious diſdaine doe men deſpiſe ſacred truths, if diſcovered in their owne native beauty and ſimplicity? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. <hi>we ſpeake wiſdome among thoſe that are perfect</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) that is, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong growne Chriſtians, who can diſcerne <hi>beauty</hi> in a <hi>plain</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, <hi>wiſedome</hi> in an <hi>Evangelicke ſimplicity;</hi> though there be no <hi>inticing words, ſublime ſpeculations,</hi> and <hi>exoticke conceits;</hi> but now carnall men are all for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>depths</hi> as they ſay, 2 <hi>Rev.</hi> 24. that is, they account them great and <hi>deep myſteries,</hi> whereas the Spirit of God accounteth them <hi>illuſions</hi> of <hi>Satan;</hi> ſurely God wil
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:161893:13"/>meet with ſuch a wanton people. The <hi>Continuator</hi> of <hi>Sleidan</hi> ſheweth, that before the great Maſſacre in <hi>France,</hi> the Proteſtants were for a luſcious wanton kind of preaching; truly we cannot abſolutely determine what will become of us, only we have cauſe to fear that <hi>Conſcientious Sermon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> as much deſpiſed as they are, may be a <hi>commodity deare</hi> enough in <hi>England</hi> ere long,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 3.4.</note> and <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> may be leſſe <hi>open,</hi> that they may be the more precious.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Plaine Apoſtaſie, and turning round to thoſe things which we hated in others before; as for inſtance, to <hi>Arminian, Antiſabbata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian doctrines,</hi> &amp;c. which heretofore were made the characteriſtick note to diſtinguiſh good perſons and bad; I would not be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, as if I did thinke a thing ſimply evill,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Paulus Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aconus.</note> becauſe held by ſuch men, oppoſition of image-worſhip, was never the worſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Monothelites</hi> firſt ſtirred in it, nor is the <hi>croſſe</hi> the more <hi>holy</hi> becauſe the <hi>Meſſalians</hi> deſpiſed it, neither is every thing evill becauſe taught by perſons whom Religion maketh juſtly odious; I only ſpeake now, as ſuppoſing other grounds, by way of ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation, and to ſhew how inexcuſable it is for us to judge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for the ſame things which we now doe our ſelves, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.3. And truly 'tis obſervable, that many, when theſe corruptions were ſet on by violence, did ſtubbornely enough bear up againſt the heat of oppoſition, whereas now by erroneous inſinuations, their revolt is made facile, ſo as they may come off from truth with the leſſe ſhame and regret, and therefore doe now allow in themſelves thoſe errours, which formerly with ſo much heat and ſharpneſſe they oppoſed in others. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.29, 30. you ſhall ſee there, of all ſinnes the Iewes were to beware of the way of the Heathens, whom God had caſt out before them; hear the words, <hi>When the Lord thy God ſhall cut off the nations from before thee, and thou goeſt and dwelleſt in their land; take heed thou be not enſnared by following them after they be deſtroyed before thee.</hi> Truly we have the ſame <hi>nature,</hi> and having the ſame <hi>poſſeſſions,</hi> may be eaſily tempted to the ſame <hi>ſinnes;</hi> as pride, looſeneſſe, eaſe, and errour, &amp;c. You that ſee that's brought as a great aggravation, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.8. <hi>they walked in the way of the Heathen, whom the Lord had caſt out before them,</hi> theſe opinions and practiſes have proved deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to others, and they will be fatall to us too; ſuch Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie is a ſinne of a double dye, as being againſt <hi>former experience</hi> of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:161893:14"/>Gods judgments on others, and the <hi>former judgment</hi> of our owne Conſciences, why were we ſo keen againſt that in them, to which we are now revolted our ſelves?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
               <hi>By the wounds</hi> Religion hath received <hi>in the houſe of her friends,</hi> many have acted of late under the <hi>name</hi> and <hi>colour of Religion,</hi> as if they went on purpoſe to make <hi>godlineſſe odious,</hi> and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>ſtinke</hi> in the land, engaging themſelves in all unwarrantable practices, odious and groſſe hereſies, proſtituting <hi>the holy profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> to all kind of impurities and injuries, whereby the mouth of iniquity is opened, the hatred of enemies juſtified, their reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches made good, and a great occaſion and advantage given to wicked men to ſpeake evill of this way; 'twas the glory of Chriſtianity heretofore to be hated unjuſtly,<note place="margin">Vide Tertull in Apol. Tali dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catore damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis noſtrae glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riamur: qui enim Neronem ſcit in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elligere po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt non niſi grande bonum a Nerone damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri. Vide notas Franciſ. Zephy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri ibidem. Divina provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentiâ effectum ut Chriſtiana Religio eos ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beret hoſtes, qui aliis virtutibus infenſi, &amp;c.</note> and that only of the worſt men, which was an argument of the goodneſſe and purity of it. That which <hi>Nero</hi> hateth muſt needs be excellent, and the only fault that could be charged upon the primitive Chriſtians, was their Chriſtianity, they were juſt and honeſt, good ſubjects and good neighbours (ſaith <hi>Pliny</hi> the younger;) only they had their <hi>hymnos Antelucanos</hi> their morning meetings to praiſe their God; and <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, the Heathens were wont to ſay <hi>Cajus Sejus vir bonus niſi quod Chriſtianus, Cajus Sejus</hi> was a good man, all his fault was, that he was a Chriſtian: you ſee ſtill their <hi>profeſſion</hi> was their only <hi>crime.</hi> Nay, to come nearer home, the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> of <hi>Aliffe</hi> in the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> confeſſed that we had <hi>orthodoxos mores,</hi> but <hi>haereticam fidem,</hi> a <hi>good life</hi> but a <hi>had beliefe;</hi> and truly this was our glory when no evill could be charged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, but our private <hi>opinion</hi> and <hi>profeſſion;</hi> but alas now 'tis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, many of thoſe that <hi>profeſſe Religion,</hi> have done that which a <hi>morall Heathen</hi> would ſcarce doe, oh what a diſhonour to Chriſt is this, that thoſe that pretend to him ſhould be leſſe civil, juſt, diſcreet &amp;c! oh how is the holy profeſſion expoſed to the ſhame and reproach of the adverſaries! how is Chriſt <hi>crucified</hi> and <hi>put to ſhame</hi> again in your <hi>ſcandals!</hi>
               <note place="margin">(a) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Naz. orat. <hi>14</hi>
               </note> how will the <hi>Chams</hi> of the world laugh to diſcover this nakedneſſe! thus it hath been of old; the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh of ſome <hi>impure deceivers,</hi> by whom the <hi>way of truth was evil ſpoken of,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. thus the <hi>ancient Chriſtians</hi> were loaded with all kind of ſcorn and contempt, and hated for the <hi>Heretickes</hi> ſake, becauſe of the <hi>Gnoſtickes</hi> they were
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:161893:14"/>called <hi>luminum extinctores</hi> putters out of the candles,<note place="margin">(b) Tertul. in Apol.</note> and doers of obſcean thinges in the dark. The unclean converſation of the <hi>Priſcillianiſts</hi> made <hi>Pagans</hi> deteſt all <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and by the rage of <hi>Maximus</hi> they fared all alike, <hi>malice</hi> will know no <hi>diſtinctione</hi> Alas,<note place="margin">(c) Dicimur Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſtiani <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. opprobrium Chriſti.</note> what a ſad thing is this, that Religions <hi>owne friends</hi> ſhould betray her, that you that are called Chriſtians, ſhould be called ſo to the diſgrace of Jeſus Chriſt, that you ſhould give occaſion to them that deſire occaſion, and make good all their reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches!</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> By Religions being made the ſtalking horſe to every ſelfe-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king deſigne, many hold it forth only out of a deſire to advance ſome private ends,<note place="margin">(d) Nunc male audiunt caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganturque phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophi noſtrae ſectae quum tue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, quod ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quà<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entibus convenit vivant, &amp; vitia ſub obtentu no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis celant. Lact. lib. de opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio dei ſub ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.</note> to get preferment and honour in the world or ſome opportunity to inrich themſelves with the publicke ſpoiles: and truly this is very ſad, that every malicious, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous or ambitious project, ſhould be cloathed with this glorious pretence: thus the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh of ſome in his dayes, that abuſed their profeſſion, by making it a <hi>cloake of maliciouſneſſe,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6. And <hi>Lactantius</hi> obſerveth the ſame alſo of many in his time, who wounded the Chriſtian name and honour by uſing it as a cover to their ſinful and corrupt practices: and others ſhew what prejudice was done to Religion, by the pride, deſire of greatneſſe, and contention, that was between the Paſtors and Profeſſours of it; inſomuch that <hi>Diocleſian</hi> thought that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity was nothing elſe but a wretched device of wicked men,<note place="margin">(e) Euſeb. lib. <hi>8.1.</hi>
               </note> ſet a foot out of ſome private aimes; thus alſo <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſpeaketh of ſome that were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſo much as <hi>Chriſt-ſellers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">(f), Ignat. Epiſt. ad Trall.</note> like <hi>Judas</hi> that followed Chriſt only to make gaine of him. I have brought theſe inſtances, becauſe they doe but give us the deſcription of many in our age, who make God <hi>to ſerve with their ſinnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 43.24.</note> and godlineſſe to be only the ſpecious out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of every unclean intent, and worldly deſigne: thus poore Religion that delighteth to breath in the aire of <hi>ſelf-deniall</hi> is made the uſuall ſtale to <hi>ſelfe-ſeeking,</hi> and godlineſſe that <hi>checketh</hi> carnall projects, by a vile ſubmiſſion is forced to ſerve them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> By the want of endeavours to propagate Religion, and to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe it amongſt others, true godlineſſe, where it is powerfull, is of a diffuſive and ſpreading nature, like leaven, till it hath pierced the whole lumpe, now what have wee done in this? either Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:161893:15"/>among their neighbours? Magiſtrates in the Kingdome? or Maſters in their Families? for private Chriſtians, they ſpend the heat and ſtrength of their ſpirits in leſſer matters, and let the weightier goe, through diviſion and ſtrife, forget edification, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny renounce all care of <hi>them without,</hi> and whereas they might have ſtrengthened the hands of their brethren, that have acted in a publicke Reformation, what have they done? have they joyned as far as their private principles would give leave? endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to bring the Kingdome onward to the way and will of Chriſt? And then for Magiſtrates, have they been ſo zealous as they ſhould bee to propagate a religious Miniſtery throughout the Kingdome, to inlighten darke corners? there is not a better worke, nor more for your ſafety.<note n="(g)" place="margin">Aug. lib. nov. de Civitate dei.</note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> obſerved that the Chriſtians taſted the violence of the <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandalls,</hi> for that they were not careful to bring off the Heathens from their Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: Such endeavours would bee your defence, and in the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe of Religion nothing concerneth you more then this, but my chief aime under this head is to ſpeak of the <hi>neglect of Family duties,</hi> which is the great reaſon why Religion is decayed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, theſe are the <hi>ſprings</hi> and <hi>fountaines</hi> of the Country, <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> were firſt in <hi>families,</hi> where the <hi>master</hi> of the houſe was the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and the beauty and power of Religion is ſtill preſerved there, and therefore next to Churches they require a chief care; Oh how excellent is it, when <hi>Churches</hi> are like to <hi>heaven,</hi> the <hi>Aſſembly below</hi> like the <hi>great Congregation above,</hi> and <hi>families</hi> like <hi>Churches</hi> for their Religion,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.29.</note> order and comelineſſe! You read of a <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Philemons houſe, Phil.</hi> 1. verſe.<note n="(h)" place="margin">Melanet. in prf at. 5 Tom oper. Lutheri.</note> 
               <hi>Melancthon</hi> ſaid of <hi>George</hi> Prince of <hi>Anhalt, Cubiculum ejus templum, Academia, Curia:</hi> that his chamber was an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> a <hi>Court,</hi> and a <hi>Church,</hi> the latter becauſe of the inſtructions, Prayer and Worſhip that was there: Religion firſt decayeth in <hi>Families</hi> before in <hi>Churches,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when the order of houſes is ſubverted, duties neglected there, how ſoon doth godlineſſe decay abroad? I doe not know any one thing that God expecteth more from a religious houſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I meane, in that capacity and relation, then the eſtabliſhment of Religion in his Family, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. <hi>I know Abraham that he will command his children and his houſhold after him to keep the way of the Lord.</hi> Mark, God reckoneth upon it as a duty that the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:161893:15"/>will perform, <hi>I know, &amp;c.</hi> and remember <hi>diſapointment</hi> is the worſt <hi>vexation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> By oppoſition and ſnarling at <hi>piety</hi> and <hi>purity,</hi> as the <hi>purity</hi> of Reformation, men are afraid to bee too heavenly, and reject <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> becauſe it would croſſe their <hi>licentiouſneſſe,</hi> and ſo the <hi>purity</hi> that ſhineth forth in the lifes of Gods ſervants,<note n="(k)" place="margin">From Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Richard Vines</hi> of the Aſſembly.</note> you heard in the morning how apt an <hi>Engliſh Spirit</hi> is to hate <hi>godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> under ſome other <hi>name,</hi> and how men that have but a <hi>Form,</hi> are wont to ſnarle at the <hi>power,</hi> and indeed the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth the ſame thing, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3. with verſe 5. <hi>having a form of godlineſſe, deſpiſers of thoſe that are good:</hi> theſe two deſcriptions are uſually coupled, <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abell</hi> both ſacrificed,<note place="margin">1 Iohn 3 12.</note> onely <hi>Abells</hi> offering was the better, and therefore <hi>Cain</hi> maliced him, men doe not love to bee upbraided by others righteouſneſſe; they would faine have their lazineſſe juſtified by the common defects, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">(l) Nazian. orat. in med.</note> they would have none zealous and excelling, therefore thoſe that are conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a form will hate thoſe that have the power, we can look for no other, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.27. <hi>Hee that was born after the fleſh, perſecuted him that was born after the Spirit, even ſo 'tis now.</hi> Wee may alſo adde, <hi>and ſo 'tis now,</hi> and ſo it will be; carnall Chriſtians will have ſome pretence or other, to perſecute thoſe that are more godly, one great deſigne is (as you heard in the morning) to cry up a name under which this hatred may bee carried on the more covertly and ſecretly, &amp; uſually it is taken from the party moſt diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced, or which is moſt publickly odious, or which hath moſt diſhonored their profeſſion: thus when the <hi>Priſcillianiſts</hi> were ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally hated, and indeed they deſerved it, other Chriſtians ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in their miſeries. <hi>Sulpitius Severus</hi> ſpeaketh of one <hi>Ithacius</hi> a Biſhop whoſe hatred againſt the <hi>Priſcillianiſts</hi> did ſo far tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port him, that if any were of good life, ſtudious of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, he would ſuſpect and blaſt him as a Priſcillianiſt. I have read of one <hi>Sanpaulinus</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Martyr, who when hee reproved one for ſwearing was preſently ſuſpected of <hi>Lutheraniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me;</hi> and <hi>Bonner,</hi> if any did but mention the name of God with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, tooke it for ground enough to call him <hi>Lollard:</hi> and true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly 'tis even thus among us, the world hath gotten ſome names and pretences, under which they carry on their hatred againſt the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:161893:16"/>power of godlineſſe the more ſecurely, and with the leſſe dread, ſo that 'tis to bee feared, that if any be of godly Converſation, it will be enough to make him a <hi>Sectary, &amp;c.</hi> an enemie of the Kingdomes peace and quiet, when the name is once gotten up, miſchiefe and malice (as I ſaid) will make no diſtinction.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> The late great increaſe of <hi>ſcandalous ſinnes,</hi> times of trouble are uſually l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>centious, and when <hi>penall lawes</hi> are ſuſpended <hi>by force, wickedneſſe</hi> groweth <hi>impudent,</hi> and truly it is even ſo among us to the confronting of authority, <hi>whoring,</hi> and <hi>ſwearing,</hi> and <hi>drunkenneſſe</hi> and <hi>Sabbath prophanations</hi> abounding every where, yea <hi>more</hi> then formerly. We looked for purging the land and 'tis more <hi>defiled,</hi> when the pot boyleth the ſcum is diſcovered, Baths bring forth corruption (if it be in the body) into the skin, God hath beene <hi>reforming</hi> the Land, and our wickedneſſe <hi>appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> the more, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.1. <hi>When I would have healed Iſrael, then the iniquity of Ephraim was diſcovered, and the wickedneſſe of Samaria.</hi> God hath been correcting and amending us, and wee have been the more vile and ſinfull. Oh then how may the Kingdome fit downe like the Church in <hi>Micah</hi> and mourne, <hi>Micah</hi> 7.1, 2. <hi>I am as when they have gathered the ſummer fruits, as the grape gleanings of the Vintage, the good man is periſhed out the of earth, there is none up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right upon the earth, they all lie in waite for blood, and hunt every man his brother by a net. Zeale</hi> is decayed, <hi>the power</hi> of godlineſſe gone, the Word deſpiſed, and wee are even growne as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whom God hath <hi>caſt out</hi> before us, Religion hath received wounds in the <hi>houſe of her friends,</hi> and is made a <hi>pretence</hi> to every baſe deſigne, few ſeek to <hi>propagate</hi> it, and it meets with much <hi>ſnarling</hi> and <hi>oppoſition</hi> every where, and iniquity is now grown <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus I have done with my firſt work, which was to ſhew wherein Religion is decayed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> My next buſineſſe is to ſhew you the <hi>occaſions</hi> and <hi>cauſes,</hi> how we came thus to <hi>languiſh</hi> and <hi>decreaſe,</hi> that ſo the <hi>guilt</hi> may lie at the <hi>right doore;</hi> and truly wee need not contend about that, but may every one of us <hi>ſmite upon the thighs,</hi> and beare the ſhame of our own iniquity.</p>
            <p>Briefly then,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For the occaſions, the knowledge of them may ſerve to ſhame
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:161893:16"/>us, with our unthankfulneſſe, they are two.</p>
            <p>One is the late proſperity which God of his mercy had given to his people, the Church,<note n="(m)" place="margin">Eceleſia haeres Crcius. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Nazian. orat. <hi>3.</hi> de pace.</note> who is the Heire of the Croſſe, is ſeldome able to manage and wield an outward happy conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I remember, <hi>(n) Nazianzen</hi> obſerveth that it hath ever with more <hi>honor endured</hi> miſery then with <hi>ſafety improved</hi> happines and ſucceſſe, that maketh us alwayes <hi>degenerate</hi> or <hi>divide;</hi> ſometimes <hi>degenerate,</hi> when <hi>Conſtantine</hi> favoured Religion, <hi>poyſon</hi> was ſowen in the Church, Chriſtians began to looſe their ancient ſeverity, and to looke after eaſe and honours and pleaſures in the World. When we have any thing in the <hi>World,</hi> we neglect out <hi>high hopes,</hi> and ſo by little and little holineſſe decayeth and degenerateth into a meere pretence, which is onely retained, the better to colour over ſome carnall purſuits and projects, whereas thoſe Chriſtians that meet with nothing but <hi>hard things</hi> in the world, and from the world, are more heavenly and holy: for the inward exerciſes of <hi>Mortification</hi> are much advantaged by their outward condition, and the world being <hi>crucified</hi> to them, they are the better <hi>crucified</hi> to the world, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Naz. ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14. <hi>(i. e.)</hi> it neither <hi>ſmileth</hi> upon them nor they upon it: and as ſucceſſe maketh us to <hi>degenerate,</hi> ſo <hi>to divide,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as hee ſaid, aſſoone as the Church grew <hi>proſperous</hi> it grew <hi>factious;</hi> like <hi>timber</hi> in the ſunſhine wee are apt to <hi>warpe</hi> and divide from one another, or like<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Quam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portaſſent tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem coronam ſi perſtitiſſent in eadem m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>litia, nec ut efferati Elephantes ab hoſtibus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſi contriviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſuos. Brightman de Luthero &amp; Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthone.</note> 
               <hi>Elephants</hi> returning from the heat of the battaile, wee tread downe our <hi>own troopes; proſperity</hi> begets <hi>wantonneſſe,</hi> and <hi>wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe novelties,</hi> &amp; ſo the people of God come to bee <hi>ſcattered,</hi> and to goe into diſtinct <hi>heards</hi> and <hi>diviſions,</hi> an evill ever <hi>fatall</hi> to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and yet it ſeemeth <hi>connaturall:</hi> the Apoſtles themſelves, though <hi>Oracles infallible,</hi> could not wholly prevent it in their dayes; outward proſperity then was a great occaſion.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Another may bee <hi>openneſſe of Viſions,</hi> carnall hearts are ſoone <hi>cloyed,</hi> I cannot tell how it commeth to paſſe, but ſo it is, the <hi>Word</hi> hath <hi>leſſe power</hi> when <hi>openly</hi> preached, a <hi>Goſpell-glutted</hi> ſtomach doth often force God to provide ſharpe remedies, either ſome <hi>great outward miſery,</hi> accompanied with the want and famine of the Word, and then any little thing is pretious, as ſee two places; one is <hi>Zech.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Yee ſhould have hearkened to the former Prophets, when Ieruſalem was inhabited and in proſperity, and the Cities thereof</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:161893:17"/>round about her, and men inhabited <hi>the South of the plain.</hi> Mark, there is their <hi>full condition</hi> deſcribed, the Temple ſtood, the City flouriſhed, the Suburbs was great, but then they hearkened not, but deſpiſed the <hi>former Prophets,</hi> that is, the Prophets that prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyed before the captivity, but now looke upon them in their <hi>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptineſſe,</hi> the other place, for that is <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.8. <hi>And now that the Lord hath ſhewed us ſuch grace to give us a naile in the holy place, &amp;c.</hi> Marke how welcome every little thing is to them then, a <hi>nayle in the holy place,</hi> is ſuch a mercy, that is, to ſee one pin or nayle driven into the rafters of the Temple, whereas before they would not know their owne mercies, whiles that ſtately Edifice ſtood in all its glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and beauty: times may come when theſe <hi>dewes</hi> will be preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and <hi>Sermon ſhowres</hi> ſweet to <hi>thirſty</hi> ſoules, or, if this bee not, God may ſend a <hi>darke Ezekiel,</hi> when a <hi>plaine Jeremy</hi> is deſpiſed, Ordinances may bee carried in ſuch an obſcure notionall aery way, as to yeeld no efficacy and comfort. Theſe are the occaſions, but what are the cauſes of the languiſhing and decay of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? I Anſwer,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> That great diviſion and diſſentiency that is among Gods owne people, when the <hi>language</hi> was divided, the <hi>building ceaſed,</hi> when Religion is <hi>controverted,</hi> it loſeth its <hi>awe</hi> and <hi>force;</hi> 'tis obſervable that <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32, 33. when the people were of one heart and of one minde, <hi>then with great power gave the Apoſtles witneſſe to the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Marke that, <hi>with power;</hi> the Word came with command and authority upon the hearts of men, the <hi>World</hi> eaſily ſtumbleth at this <hi>rock of offence,</hi> the Aſſent is more looſe and doubtfull when things are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the uncertainty of diſputes, and ſo doth not command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly check vitious inclinations: when the wayes of fleſh and blood, are backed with wit and parts, and made to ſeeme a valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able opinion, men are hardly gained.</p>
            <p>Beſides, godly men themſelves while they ingage with too much heat and zeale in their particular opinions, grow coole in piety and practicall duties, the ſtrength of their ſpirits being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, and carryed out ſo diſproportionably to the leſſer mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; God placed the <hi>Flaming Sword</hi> about <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> and the Goſpel calleth for violence in the <hi>matters of the Kingdome, Matth.</hi> 11.12. but wee uſually miſtake our object, and miſplace our zeale upon ſuch matters as have more of <hi>intereſt</hi> in them
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:161893:17"/>then <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> and are rather buſied in <hi>diſputing much,</hi> then <hi>doing much.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The embaſting and emaſculating the Ordinance of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>hunger</hi> ſeeketh <hi>food,</hi> but <hi>luſt dainties</hi> and <hi>quailes;</hi> when Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers provide for mens <hi>luſts</hi> rather then their <hi>conſciences,</hi> Religion is embaſed, &amp; loſeth power. A Miniſtery that ſtayeth in the <hi>paint of words</hi> will beget but <hi>painted grace,</hi> when we come in the <hi>demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirit,</hi> we come in <hi>power,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> with plain and ſolid conviction, <hi>this is the ſinne, this the curſe and miſery.</hi> When the thread of the Goſpel is ſo <hi>fine ſpun,</hi> 'twill not <hi>cloath</hi> a naked ſoule, <hi>notion</hi> eateth out all <hi>ſaving knowledge,</hi> the Apoſtle ſpeaks of a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.20. <hi>oppoſitions of ſcience falſly ſo called,</hi> by which they thought to <hi>better</hi> the Goſpel, but did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>debaſe</hi> it: ſuch niceties <hi>enervate</hi> godlineſſe, make it weak and leſs in power; we muſt take heed then of debaſing this Ordinance to an <hi>effeminate delicacy,</hi> it ſhould ſtill be <hi>maſculine</hi> and generous, full of <hi>Spirit,</hi> and <hi>power from on high.</hi> I would not bee miſtaken as if I did plead for a lazy careleſneſſe in managing the Word, I know that God concurreth with mans diligence, and if wee would not have the people loath the Word, wee ſhould painfully provide it for them; every <hi>Scribe that is inſtructed for the Kingdome of God,</hi> that is, that would doe ſervice in the Church of God, <hi>muſt bring forth out of his treaſuries things both new and old, Matth.</hi> 13.52. that is, although not new truths, yet <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, old <hi>Truths</hi> in a new <hi>way,</hi> otherwiſe repreſented to the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or fancy, to take of that <hi>taedium</hi> or naturall ſatiety that is in us, that wee may not loath them as <hi>Coleworts twice ſod,</hi> but that truths may ſtill have a freſh look upon the conſcience and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. This may be done, but wee muſt take heed of <hi>ungrounded ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceties, ſubtle notions,</hi> that beget onely <hi>ſpeculation</hi> and doe not ſtirre up to <hi>practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> An <hi>undue</hi> preaching of the Goſpel, <hi>poyſon</hi> conveyed in ſo <hi>ſweet a wine,</hi> maketh the cup the more deadly; by this means,<hi>Religion</hi> it ſelfe is made to bee of <hi>ſins ſide,</hi> and the <hi>grace</hi> of God plyable to <hi>carnall</hi> concluſions; and indeed when the truths of God that ſhould <hi>convince of ſinne,</hi> are debauched to ſo vile a purpoſe as to <hi>countenance ſinne,</hi> men can the better overcome <hi>remorſe</hi> of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and doe ſinne with the <hi>leſſe regret,</hi> out of a preſumption, that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:161893:18"/>the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is of their ſide, <hi>Jude</hi> Verſ. 3. <hi>They turne the grace of our God into wantonneſſe,</hi> they debauch the <hi>grace of God,</hi> that is, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of grace, make that yeeld countenance to their luſts, and ſo men father their <hi>Baſtards</hi> upon the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and ſinne <hi>cum pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilegin</hi> by a <hi>licence</hi> from heaven. When thoſe that ſhould have been Prophets cryed <hi>peace, peace,</hi> ſee what <hi>Jeremy</hi> ſaith, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.10. Ah <hi>Lord God, ſurely thou haſt greatly deceived this people, in ſaying they ſhall have peace.</hi> 'Twas done in Gods name by the falſe Prophets, and they were as ſecure as if God himſelfe had ſaid ſo: Wee would willingly have the Goſpel <hi>over Goſpeld,</hi> and hear in the eare of liberty, therefore I am perſwaded there is no one thing hath hindered the power of godlineſſe, care of duty, <hi>humbling of ſoules,</hi> ſo much as this, undue preaching of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Publicke liberty and connivence that maketh ſin <hi>more common</hi> and ſo <hi>leſſe odious,</hi> outward reſtraints keep men that are evill from diſcovering of it, and though it bee the priviledge of divine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts to <hi>convert the ſoule, Pſal.</hi> 19.7. yet the commands and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of men may much hinder the <hi>diffuſion</hi> and <hi>diſſemination</hi> of ſin and errour; 'tis good to obſerve the ſeverall <hi>guards</hi> that God hath put upon a man to keep him from ſinne (ſo prone are wee to it:) there are <hi>inward guards,</hi> Spirit, Word and Conſcience; there are <hi>outward guards,</hi> the Miniſtery, the Church, and the Magiſtrate; all which are as in his ſtead to bee an <hi>awe</hi> to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, more eſpecially it is ſaid of the Magiſtrate that hee is <hi>the Miniſter of God to bee a terrour to evill doers, Rom.</hi> 13.3, 4. Now when their ſword is ſheathed up, and nothing is ſetled, wicked men loſe all awe and reſtraint, and doe what is <hi>right in their own eyes, Judges</hi> 21.25. as 'tis ſaid there they did, when there <hi>was no King in Iſrael,</hi> that is, no exerciſe of Government to reſtrain publicke diſorders, (for as yet their Government was not <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchicall</hi>) then all goeth to wrack, iniquity groweth impudent, and Religion is borne downe, <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.8. <hi>A King that ſitteth upon the throne of judgment ſcattereth away all evill with his eyes:</hi> that is, when Magiſtrates imploy and draw out their power, they ſcatter evill, as the Sun ſcattereth miſts.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Another cauſe may bee want of <hi>Catechiſing,</hi> by which means truths would be more revived, and kept freſh and ſavory in the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:161893:18"/>thoughts, and ſo have the more awe upon us. <hi>Martyrology</hi> and <hi>Catechiſing</hi> were two of the moſt ſucceſſefull engines againſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery. Truths worke moſt when we diſcerne that <hi>Cognation</hi> and <hi>kin,</hi> by which they touch and reſpect one another; <hi>indiſtinct knowledge</hi> doth but diſpoſe to <hi>error</hi> or <hi>looſeneſſe;</hi> Sermon <hi>hints,</hi> an <hi>hint</hi> here, and an <hi>hint</hi> there, doth not ſo much good, for men of weaker conceits cannot ſo eaſily diſcerne how one truth is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred from another, and what analogy and proportion there is between them, and ſo are eaſily overcome by more ſubtile and ſtronger wits; or elſe not diſcerning that faire complyance that is between practical and comfortable truths, grow looſe: certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Religion would be more propagated if this exerciſe were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived. We are debtors to <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>unwiſe, Rom.</hi> 1.14. and Chriſt that bade <hi>Peter</hi> feed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>his ſheep,</hi> bade him alſo feed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>his lambes, John</hi> 21.15, 16. For want of this pattern of ſound words, and theſe condeſcenſions to weake ones by this exerciſe, many miſchiefs have abounded amongſt us to the great dammage of Religion and godlineſſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe are part of the cauſes, others might bee mentioned, but I ſhall forbeare: you will ſay then, What remedy? there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall proceed to the next thing, which is to ſhew you,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> What we ſhould doe to <hi>ſtrengthen the things that are ready to die,</hi> or to repaire decayed godlineſſe; give mee leave to ſpeake a word,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> To all in generall, as we are Chriſtians; ſeverall things are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; let me point at a few.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Oh that we would all joyn together, <hi>quaſi manu factá</hi> ('tis <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullians</hi> word) in an holy conſpiracy to befiege heaven by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, untill more <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>life</hi> be powred out, and in greater abundance; God hath ſaid,<note place="margin">Acts 2.15.</note> that he will <hi>powre out his Spirit upon all fleſh;</hi> oh beg it for <hi>England,</hi> goe to him that hath <hi>the ſeven Spirits,</hi> to look upon <hi>another dead Sardis.</hi> God muſt <hi>offer violence</hi> to us, ere we can <hi>offer violence to the Kingdom;</hi> 'tis the mighty <hi>quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Spirit,</hi> that muſt revive us in our <hi>languiſhings;</hi> that which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth the ſoule to <hi>God,</hi> muſt come from <hi>God,</hi> waters can ariſe no higher then their ſpring: Religion is like the pure <hi>Veſtall flame,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:161893:19"/>which if it went out, was to be kindled only by a <hi>ſun-beam;</hi> oh then let us goe and wait before God, for thoſe <hi>ſeven Spirits,</hi> thoſe mighty and quickning operaions! the <hi>Spirit</hi> came upon Chriſt in the appearance of a <hi>dove,</hi> to ſhew his <hi>meekneſſe,</hi> but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Apoſtles in <hi>cloven tongues of fire,</hi> to ſhew the <hi>might</hi> and <hi>force</hi> that is in his operations.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Let us ſtudy how we may more honour and adorne Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by a godly and peaceable walking before God and men. Every <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ſhould be the Goſpels <hi>ornament,</hi> as an <hi>Hypocrite</hi> is the Goſpels <hi>diſgrace, Tit.</hi> 2.10. <hi>adorne the doctrine of God our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our:</hi> let the world know there is more in Religion then pretence and policy, whiles hypocrites and ſuch as ſeek themſelves betray the honour of Religion, doe you advance it, let them ſee there are true <hi>ſtarres</hi> as well as glaring <hi>mete ors,</hi> your lives ſhould make God glorious, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. hold forth the <hi>praiſes</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>of him that hath called you,</hi> let them read God in you of a truth, and be not diſtinguiſhed ſo much by a <hi>party</hi> and <hi>profeſſion</hi> as by <hi>holineſſe, Tertullian</hi> ſaith of the ancient Chriſtians, <hi>Non aliunde noſcibiles quam de emendatione vitiorum,</hi> their <hi>diſtinction</hi> was their <hi>innocency.</hi> When divers Libertines had diſhonoured Religion, and walked unworthily in their relations, <hi>Peter</hi> preſſeth the true Chriſtians to good conſcience and more honeſt walking, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. indeed both thoſe Chapters are to this purpoſe, this will bee a <hi>reall</hi> confutation, and then God will give you praiſe in the land of your ſhame; haire cut will grow again, if the roots remain,<note place="margin">Zeph. 3.19.</note> and though the razor of cenſure hath brought baldneſſe and reproach upon the head of Religion, yet its good name will grow and flouriſh again, and they wil be aſhamed that <hi>falſly accuſe your godly converſation.</hi> Oh, brethren at ſuch times we ſhould walke with more care! it's a ſmart queſtion that <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Ought yee not to walke in the feare of our God, becauſe of the repreach of the Heathen our adverſaries?</hi> when your lives are thus ſleek and innocent, this dirt will not ſtick.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Stirre up your ſelves, and provoke one another to more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe in dead times: we ſhould ſtrive who ſhould be firſt, and exceed in godlineſſe, you know that noted place, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.24. <hi>Let us conſider one another, to provoke unto love and good workes;</hi> this is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> an holy contention, when we contend who ſhall be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:161893:19"/>moſt forward in the matters of God; we often provoke one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother to carnall ſtrife, to exceſſe in vanity; oh when doe wee ſharpen and whet each others graces? the <hi>ſonnes of the coale,</hi> how doe they <hi>inkindle</hi> one another, and ſtrengthen each others hands in wickedneſſe? ſee how the Idolaters are deſcribed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.6, 7. <hi>They helped every one his neighhour, every one ſaid to his brother, Be of good courage. So the Carpenter incouraged the Goldſmith, and hee that ſmootheth with the hammer, him that ſmiteth on the Anvill, &amp;c.</hi> the prophet ſpeaketh of the time, when the Goſpel was ſent to the <hi>Iſles,</hi> ver. 1. that is, to the <hi>European Countreys</hi> which are uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſed by <hi>Iſles</hi> in <hi>Iſay.</hi> Now as ſoon as they liſtned to this Doctrine, downe went the pictures and the images, but there being ſome hope offered of their re-erection, they come and ſtrengthen one anothers hand, <hi>Be of good courage,</hi> they hoped to bring up their craft and way again with pompe and triumph: Oh when they ſtrenghthen one another, will not you?<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Naz. orat. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzen</hi> was wont to call the enemies of the Church <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the common reconcilers;</hi> becauſe when they unite and ſupport one another againſt the Church, it doth but invite the people of God to a more cloſe union, and free communion with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; this would be an excellent way to prevent the decayes of love and piety.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Delight in, &amp; wait upon the powerful miniſtery of the word, <hi>The prophets propheſie lies, and the people love to have it ſo, Ier.</hi> 5.31. A vaine <hi>people</hi> do but incourage a vain <hi>Miniſtery.</hi> Doe not delight then in a glozing diſpenſation, 'twil be ſucceſſeleſſe, frothy ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations, morall ſtrains do no good, the people begin to grow weary of ſavory and ſound knowledg; the <hi>teſtimony</hi> of the <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> was a <hi>torment</hi> to the <hi>dwellers on the earth, Rev.</hi> 11.10. power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full preaching is their burden. The lazy world would faine lye upon the bed of eaſe, draw the curtains and reſt, and therefore <hi>light</hi> is troubleſome, men begin to thirſt and pant for the old <hi>unſavory morall ſtraines,</hi> which remain in wary generalls, and do not irritate, the Lord may give you your deſire, but remember that's a <hi>carnallitch</hi> that muſt be <hi>clawed,</hi> and the times will be ſad, when men cannot <hi>endure ſound doctrine,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3.</p>
            <p>I have doe with my addreſſe to the people.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> I ſhall ſpeak a word to the Miniſtery, I am the worſt of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:161893:20"/>to direct others, only I ſhall take the liberty in all humility to ſuggeſt my thoughts. Much may be done by you to the repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of decayed godlineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> muſt ſtill be preached, that's the main truth, that kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth in the <hi>life</hi> of Chriſtianity; the more <hi>Evangelicall</hi> diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are, the more <hi>powerfull;</hi> our beloved muſt ſtill be kept as a <hi>bundle of Myrrhe</hi> next our hearts, 1 <hi>Cant.</hi> 13. ſtill freſh and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant in the thoughts, all the comfort and ſupport of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an dependeth upon that, this is the very ſpirit and flower of any Miniſtery, and therefore 'tis ſaid <hi>Apoc.</hi> 19.10. <hi>the Teſtimony of Jeſus is the Spirit of propheſie,</hi> it is not only the <hi>beauty,</hi> but the <hi>life</hi> of any diſpenſation; I know many thinke this needleſſe, for as I ſaid before, the <hi>indiſtinct,</hi> and <hi>undue</hi> preaching of Chriſt, is the cauſe of all the <hi>looſeneſſe</hi> and <hi>vanity</hi> into which Religion is degenerated. I but I adde here, that this diſpenſation is ſtill need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, the fooliſh world is apt to flye into extreames, ſome are all for doctrines of Chriſt, others will heare nothing of him, becauſe theſe ſweet truths have been ſo much miſapplyed. Popery got up by this pretence, they would not open that gap of <hi>free-grace</hi> to the <hi>people; Paul</hi> would preach the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt though many did abuſe it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8. <hi>ſome ſlaunderouſly report that we ſay, Let us doe evill that good may come thereof, whoſe damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is just;</hi> the meaning is, ſome gave out that <hi>Paul</hi> taught that they might ſinne freely, that God might have the more glory in pardoning; which is expreſſed there, by <hi>doing evill that good may come of it;</hi> now ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>their damnation is juſt;</hi> that is, if they undoe themſelves with ſuch a vile conceit, they may thanke themſelves, they never learned it from me; if poyſon be ſucked out of the flower, thanke the ſpider, and if <hi>precious liquor</hi> be ſowred, 'tis becauſe of the <hi>uncleanneſſe</hi> of the veſſel. <hi>Muſculus</hi> in one of his bookes had ſaid, That no places were ſo prophane and irreligious, as thoſe where the Goſpel had been preached; or words to that effect. And <hi>Contzen</hi> a Jeſuite crieth out upon this, <hi>Hi ſunt Evangelici Doctores,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Adam Contzen in <hi>Mat.</hi> c. <hi>24.5.</hi>
               </note> ſee the fruit of <hi>Proteſtantiſm</hi> and <hi>Goſpel-preaching!</hi> Many are of his ſpirit, maligne and ſlaunder a Goſpel-diſpenſation; Alas, we are not <hi>in the place of God,</hi> to prevent miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apprehenſions; it is our duty to keepe this truth freſh in the thoughts, to offer it as a <hi>bundle of Myrrh</hi> to the Spouſes boſome.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:161893:20"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Humbling doctrines muſt be duly preſſed, <hi>John Baptiſt levelled</hi> mountaines, and in his dayes much <hi>violence</hi> was offered to the Kingdome, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.12. and indeed, ſtill <hi>John</hi> muſt goe before <hi>Jeſus;</hi> like the day-ſtar before the ſun, <hi>Moſes</hi> led the people in the <hi>wilderneſſe,</hi> before <hi>Joſhua</hi> led them into the land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> we muſt awaken firſt by a <hi>ſenſe of wrath,</hi> or elſe they will not care for a <hi>ſight of mercy;</hi> the people did not deſire a <hi>Mediatour</hi> till they heard the <hi>thundring, Exod.</hi> 20.18.19. and 'tis Gods uſuall method to ſuffer us to be <hi>dead to one law,</hi> ere we are <hi>alive to another, Gal.</hi> 2.19. firſt to make us underſtand the <hi>ſevere obligation</hi> that is upon us by the <hi>Covenant of workes,</hi> ere wee are brought into a <hi>better hope</hi> by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> God is never truly <hi>exalted</hi> in the ſoule till man be <hi>humbled; Dagon</hi> muſt <hi>fall</hi> and be <hi>broken,</hi> if the <hi>Arke</hi> bee <hi>ſet up.</hi> The Lord diggeth <hi>deep,</hi> when he meaneth to raiſe the building <hi>high,</hi> and when hee will bring off the ſoule to Chriſt powerfully, he bringeth them out of themſelves by godly ſorrow. This is the drift and ſcope of the whole Scriptures, and therefore I uſe the leſſe of argument in this matter.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Among other parts of godlineſſe, it ſeemeth to be moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary now to preſſe the <hi>duties of relations:</hi> I ſay, to preſſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to carry themſelves holily in their civill relations: no way provideth for the diſcharge of the duties of relations, ſo much as Chriſtianity, or Religion, and none have failed in them ſo much as religious perſons of late, ſo that a great deale of diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour hath come to God, and a great deale of prejudice to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,<note place="margin">Dent exercium talem qualem doctrina Chriſti milites eſſe juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi, tales Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciales, tales Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, tales Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minos, talet Fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os, tales Servos, tales Reges, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Iudices, tales denique debito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum redditores, &amp; exactores ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius fiſci, &amp;c. Aug. ad Marcelo ep. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> by our unworthy walking in our civill relations, the Goſpel or law of Chriſt requireth that theſe civil reſpects which we owe to men, ſhould be diſcharged, as in and to the Lord, and that we ſhould turne duties of the <hi>ſecond table,</hi> into duties of the <hi>firſt;</hi> that is, performe <hi>civil</hi> reſpects upon a <hi>religious</hi> ground. So that it hath been the glory and honour of Religion heretofore, to yeild the <hi>beſt</hi> children, the <hi>beſt</hi> ſubjects, the <hi>beſt</hi> Kings, the <hi>beſt</hi> husbands and wives in the world. Therefore <hi>Auguſtine</hi> maketh a challenge to all the world, <hi>Dent exercitum talem quatem doctrina Chriſti milites eſſe juſſit,</hi> Let all the world (ſaith he) yeild ſuch Children, ſuch Subjects, ſuch Souldiers, ſuch Servants, ſuch an Army, ſuch Provincialls, Judges, Kings, ſuch faithfull ones, when they have been intruſted with the publicke moneys; (but
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:161893:21"/>alas, the caſe is quite otherwiſe, of late none worſe then they, none more apt to diſhonour God in <hi>relations,</hi> to diſturbe civill peace, to reſiſt Magiſtracy upon every diſ-ſatisfaction, and to make every diſcontent the ground of commotion and diſobedience, therefore to teach men to improve their relations for the glory of God and good of Religion, muſt needs bee ſeaſonable, that if it be poſſible wee may repair that <hi>incomparable loſſe,</hi> which Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath ſuſtained this way.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Learn that holy art of <hi>compounding</hi> peace wieh purity, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may loſe its due reſpect, that we may neither hazard Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion by <hi>ſilence</hi> nor <hi>eager contention; Holineſſe</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> are daughters of the ſame ſpirit and may bee reconciled, you finde them often coupled in Scripture, <hi>James</hi> 3.17. <hi>The wiſdome that is from above is firſt pure and then peaceable: purity</hi> muſt have the precedence in your endeavours, but <hi>peaceableneſſe</hi> muſt not altogether bee ſhut out; ſo <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.30. Have ſalt in your ſelves and peace one with another, <hi>Salt</hi> and peace bee <hi>ſavoury,</hi> but not too tart and <hi>auſtere.</hi> I will not <hi>direct</hi> my Brethren, I doe onely <hi>ſuggeſt</hi> it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> One Word now to the Magiſtrate, and I have done, Oh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this matter appertaineth to you, <hi>to strengthen things that are ready to dye,</hi> to repaire decayed godlineſſe, this challengeth a chief care, yea <hi>the firſt place</hi> in your debates; as in the Commandements, <hi>Spirituall</hi> duties have the precedency of <hi>Morall.</hi> In the name of Chriſt then let me beſeech you,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> To bee holy and godly in your <hi>own perſons,</hi> Oh how ſad will it bee for your ſoules in the day of the Lord, if you ſhould be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the Reformation of <hi>others</hi> and not bee reformed <hi>your ſelves,</hi> that you ſhould be like <hi>Noah's ſhipwrights</hi> that frame an <hi>Arke</hi> for others and periſh in the waters your ſelves, or like the <hi>Jews</hi> that directed the wiſe men to <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> but went not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves thither to worſhip <hi>Chriſt!</hi> O conſider you are the <hi>firſt ſheets</hi> of the Kingdom, others are printed after your <hi>copy,</hi> if the firſt ſheet be well ſet, a thouſand more are ſtamped with eaſe: ſee then that the power of Religion prevaile over your own ſouls: that after you have done good to others you may not be <hi>caſtawayes:</hi> How can men think you are ſincere in eſtabliſhing of Religion, if it hath made no impreſſion on your own hearts? Scandalous Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and wicked Magiſtrates doe but pull down with one hand what they ſet up with the other.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:161893:21"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> If you would repaire Religion and promote godlyneſſe, give incouragement to a godly Miniſtry, you ſee when Chriſt wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to the Church to repaire godlineſſe, he directeth it to the <hi>Angell,</hi> Oh let there bee an Angell in every Church, Chriſts ſtrength lyeth in his mouth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.2. That's the Sword by which hee overcometh the World, 'tis the weapon hee uſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Antichriſt, the <hi>Spirit of his mouth,</hi> as <hi>Gideon</hi> overcame the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> by <hi>lampes in pitchers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſo doth Chriſt by <hi>lampes and pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,</hi> and therefore the Apoſtle calleth it light, or treaſure <hi>in an earthen veſſel;</hi> Oh then maintaine the lampe that they may bee a meanes in the hand of God of maintaining godlyneſſe in the Kingdome, let there bee (as I ſaid) an <hi>Angell</hi> in every <hi>Church,</hi> a <hi>light</hi> in every <hi>ſocket,</hi> a <hi>ſtarre</hi> in every <hi>orbe,</hi> if you looke abroad you will find many continued through favor &amp; mediation of friends,<note place="margin">Brightman in L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c.</note> 
               <hi>Qui nihil babent in vita Angelicum aut in doctrina Evangelicum,</hi> that have nothing <hi>Angelicall</hi> in their life or <hi>Evangelicall</hi> in their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Heartily eſtabliſh an holy Government in the Church, <hi>order</hi> and <hi>diſcipline</hi> is the <hi>fence</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> and a Church well governed is <hi>terrible as an Army with Banners, Cant.</hi> 6.4. that is, full of beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſtrength, Armies ordered are comely and in a capacity to fight, the preſent <hi>decayes</hi> are by <hi>confuſion,</hi> 'tis ſaid <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.35. <hi>Thou art terrible out of thy holy places,</hi> in the order and beauty of the Church God is moſt terrible, when worſhip is pure and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar it impreſſeth a dread and a reverence upon men.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Countenance godly perſons, they are a Kingdomes beſt ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.5. and the Governours of <hi>Judah</hi> ſhall ſay in their hearts, The inhabitants of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> are my ſtrength in the Lord of Hoſts their God. Mark, you ſhould call them your ſtrength, they ingage a bleſſing; when <hi>Lot</hi> was in <hi>Sodome, Sodome</hi> was in <hi>Lot,</hi> this is one of your chief duties, to ſee that godlineſſe live peaceably, wee are bound to pray for you upon this ground, <hi>Pray for them that are in Authority, that wee may leade a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſſe and honeſty,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. Oh look to it then, that religion may have a quiet abode, or elſe you wil not.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Honour and ſweeten Religion by ſome releaſe of the peoples burdens, Belly arguments doe worke much upon them, <hi>Ier.</hi> 44.17. <hi>Wee will burn incenſe to the Queen of heaven, for then wee had
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:161893:22"/>plenty of victualls, and were well and ſaw no evill.</hi> They meaſure Religion by their outward concernments, and judge of wayes by their burdens and troubles. The oppreſſion of ſome Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant princes in <hi>Germany</hi> was a ſcandall to the Reformation, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſtirreth up vulgar hatred and introduceth violent changes ſo much as this: the people are like the <hi>read of Egypt,</hi> if wee lean too hard, they doe not <hi>ſupport</hi> but <hi>pierce,</hi> and oppreſſion is like an iron in the fire, 'twill <hi>burn</hi> their fingers that hold it: I confeſſe this is ſomewhat out of my way, therefore I was the more loath to ſpeak in it, but it being for Religions ſake, I hope you will pardon an humble motion.</p>
            <p>I ſhall but hint two Motives to ſet on all and conclude,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Is that in the 3. verſe of this Chapter, leſt I <hi>come as a thief,</hi> oh conſider Chriſt may ſteale upon you, when hee taketh off his reſtraint from a people, and they break out into <hi>tumults,</hi> 'tis a ſhrewd ſigne, you know what faction was ruined by tumults, 'tis an unhappy preſage.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The next is taken from the 4. verſe, <hi>Thou hast a few names that have not defiled their Garments.</hi> God taketh notice of thoſe few names that are zealous for him in <hi>dead times,</hi> that minde the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of piety whilſt others debaſe it, they ſhall <hi>walke with mee in white;</hi> either God will provide an Arke of ſafety for you, for the preſent, or give you heaven, which ſhall make amends for all.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
